<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Indulgence not justified being a continuation of the Discourse of toleration, in answer to the arguments of a late book entituled A peace-offering, or plea for indulgence, and to the cavils of another call'd The second discourse of the religion in England.</title>
            <author>Perrinchief, Richard, 1623?-1673.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1668</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 133 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 27 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A54407</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P1594</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R26874</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09570748</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09570748</idno>
            <idno type="VID">43664</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A54407)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 43664)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1337:31)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Indulgence not justified being a continuation of the Discourse of toleration, in answer to the arguments of a late book entituled A peace-offering, or plea for indulgence, and to the cavils of another call'd The second discourse of the religion in England.</title>
                  <author>Perrinchief, Richard, 1623?-1673.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>51 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for R. Royston and James Collins,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1668.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title: A continuation of the Discourse of toleration.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Richard Perrinchief--NUC pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Corbet, John, 1620-1680. --  Second discourse of the religion of England.</term>
               <term>Owen, John, 1616-1683. --  Peace-offering in an apology and humble plea for indulgence and liberty of conscience.</term>
               <term>Liberty of conscience.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:43664:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:43664:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>INDULGENCE not JUSTIFIED:</hi> Being a Continuation of the DISCOURSE OF TOLERATION: In Anſwer to the ARGUMENTS Of a late Book, Entituled <hi>A Peace-Offering,</hi> or <hi>Plea for Indulgence:</hi> And to the CAVILS Of another, call'd <hi>The Second Diſcourſe of the Religion in</hi> England.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Auguſt. Epiſt. Quinquageſ. ad Boniſacium.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Quomodo Reges Domino ſerviunt in timore, niſi ea quae contra juſſa Domini fiunt, Religioſâ ſeveritate prohibendo atque plectendo?</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>R. Royſton</hi> and <hi>James Collins,</hi> MDCLXVIII.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb facs="tcp:43664:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:43664:2"/>
            <head>A CONTINUATION OF THE DISCOURSE OF TOLERATION.</head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 1. <hi>Our Laws for <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity juſtifiable.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>REligion being acknowledged by the Experience of all ages to have an effectual Influence upon the civil Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation of men, the meaſures of a Peoples mutual Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence, and ſo conſequently of their Quiet among themſelves, will be according to the Degrees of Purity, and Unity, which are obſerved in that Religion, profeſſed by the State. <hi>Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity</hi> though it be the only true and pure Religion, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore where it is obſerved in its Simplicity, is moſt beneficial to mankind; for all its precepts oblige Beleevers to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acteſt Juſtice, the moſt compaſſionate acts of Mercy, and the ſtricteſt Peace, by which Societies are preſerved and advanced: Yet being to be profeſſed by men encompaſſed with Infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and not ſecured from Corruptions, it is obnoxious to <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies,</hi> and <hi>Diviſions;</hi> becauſe there will be alwaies ignorant and unſtable men who will wreſt the Scriptures to their own damnation, and there will be men of corrupt minds, who ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving put away a good Conſcience, concerning the Faith will make ſhipwrack. And when Contentions ariſe in this, they are more bitter and fierce then upon any other account, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Honour of God ſeems concerned in the Quarrel, and the glory of Heaven is conceived the Prize for the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:43664:3"/>Zeale. Therefore all <hi>Chriſtian Princes,</hi> have ſeen a neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to preſerve as much as they could the Unity of Religion as one of the Foundations of their Subjects Peace: And when Diviſions have happened within their Territories, by conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſuch Perſons who might be preſumed the fitteſt Judges in the Caſe, they have ſearched for the Truth; which being once found, they have maintained it by a reſtraint upon all Contradictions to it.</p>
               <p>This hath been the known practice of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Princes ſince the <hi>Reformation,</hi> by which they kept the Diſſentions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Latitude and Extent of Reformation in ſo low a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, that though they required the publick Cares; yet they did never effect any common Trouble, till this our laſt Age: in which men grew weary of their Peace, and glutted with too great a Proſperity (the chief cauſe of all Civil Wars) they grew impatient of Laws; and not ſatisfied with that juſt Liberty, wherein they enjoyed their private Rights with as great, if not greater ſecurity, as any Nation under the Sun, they invaded thoſe of the Throne.</p>
               <p>Their method to ſuch an Enterprize was to cauſe a Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, in which they hoped by baſe Arts to form their For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes agreeable to their Luſts. To introduce Diſorder they firſt attempted upon Religion, and by ruining and diſſolving the Government of the Church they opened a breach for all Hereſies, and incouraged all Schiſms: Thus they got a party ingaged to them for their Licence, and by their force and fraud a Power, which through the juſt Judgment of the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous God, attained their Curſed ends.</p>
               <p>But when it pleaſed the Almighty Goodneſs by breaking them to pieces with his own arme to reſtore our <hi>Rightful</hi> Prince, and our ancient Laws; to aſcertain our Peace, thoſe juſt rules of Government to effect Unity in Religion, were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain practiſed; <hi>His Majeſty</hi> and <hi>the Parliament</hi> enacting ſuch Laws as did enjoin <hi>Uniformity</hi> in Religion. In making of which as they did cut off all thoſe Jealouſies (which are dangerous to Magiſtrates) of being unconcerned for the Worſhip of God; So in the Laws themſelves they have prevented all Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumnies of Cruelty and Perſecution.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:43664:3"/>
For by them <hi>No man is forced to profeſſe any thing contrary to his Perſwaſion,</hi> which he calls his Faith. <hi>No man is denied the Liberty of his own Worſhip in his own Family,</hi> with ſo li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited a Company as may not enjealous the State of contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a Publick Diſturbance.</p>
               <p>Beſides <hi>there is no Condition impoſed upon our Communion but Conformity with the Church as to the Outward part of Worſhip, without any expreſs or formal Declaration of their Opinions con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning it.</hi> And by this Moderation all the clamours of <hi>Force</hi> upon <hi>Conſcience,</hi> and <hi>Compulſion to the Faith,</hi> are rendred falſe and unreaſonable.</p>
               <p>All that theſe Laws extend unto, is to <hi>ſecure</hi> the <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Peace;</hi> 1. <hi>By forbidding any to be admitted to the Office of Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers and Miniſters, but ſuch who ſecure the Church and State by their Subſcriptions or Oaths, that they will not hold or teach any thing contrary to the Publick profeſſion: and that they will conſent to the Uſe of the preſcribed Forms of Worſhip.</hi> 2. <hi>By hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering of Conventicles and meetings, wherein ſuch Errors might be publiſhed, and the publick Tranquillity deſigned againſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Which Laws as they are juſtifiable by the continued pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of the Church in all Ages, by the Examples of the moſt Religious Princes: ſo alſo are they far beneath that rigour which the men who now complain of them, did uſe when and where, they had or have power. Who has forgot the <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannies</hi> of the <hi>Covenant?</hi> We have heard of the Terrors whereby the Decrees of the <hi>Kirk of Scotland</hi> exacted Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. And <hi>New England</hi> ſhews us what we were to have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected from the <hi>Independents</hi> here, had they attained to the iſſue of their Deſigns (which they ſpeedily haſted unto) and gotten a fixed power amongſt us. But how juſt ſoever the Laws are in themſelves, yet becauſe they are againſt the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of men of unlawful Hopes, and they obſtruct the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of that Grandeur which others had in our miſeries, they have been written againſt in ſeveral books; more particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in one intituled a <hi>Diſcourſe of Religion,</hi> as not having ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tled Reformed Chriſtianity in its due Latitude, nor provided for the Stability and Advancement of this Kingdome. To juſtifie the Counſels of our Law-givers in theſe Acts, there
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:43664:4"/>was publiſhed <hi>a Diſcourſe of Toleration</hi> in anſwer to that <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of Religion,</hi> which was to ſhew, <hi>That the Cauſes of Diſſentions in Religion, which are the Subject of Tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, being infamous and ſinful, and their Effects full of Deſtruction to Piety, and the Common-Wealth; That there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore every one was bound in their Place, and Order, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour their Removal and Extirpation; And that this was not to be effected by Toleration,</hi> was proved by ſeveral Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, and by ſhewing the weakneſs of all thoſe reaſons which were urged in the <hi>Diſcourſe of Religion.</hi> Since that, there is come forth another Book entituled a <hi>Peace Offering, or Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy and Plea for Indulgence,</hi> which proceeds upon other grounds to ſhew that all <hi>External Force by Civil Laws upon the account of Religion is not to be juſtified.</hi> To adjuſt therefore that <hi>Diſcourſe of Toleration</hi> againſt all the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that are brought in the <hi>Apology</hi> for <hi>Indulgenee,</hi> and to vindicate it from the <hi>Exceptions</hi> made to it in a <hi>ſecond Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of Religion</hi> is the buſineſſe of this preſent Treatiſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 2. <hi>An Anſwer to the Book called the Peace-Offering, That Indulgence is not juſtified by the Law of Nature.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Book called the <hi>Peace-Offering</hi> bears the name of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral <hi>Proteſtants;</hi> but what ſort or party of Proteſtants it leaves us to conjecture. Some paſſages in it perſwade us that they are <hi>Independents,</hi> but they being ſo comprehenſive a Sect of thoſe ſtrictly ſo called, and of the other who crowd under that name, as <hi>Anabaptiſts, Socinians, Antinomians,</hi> &amp;c. We are ſtill in the dark what ſort of men they are; therefore we can take no notice of that great kindneſs they ſhow to themſelves, in being free in their own commendations. Nor will we of their Principles, they being various, according to the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Sects, and ſtill changeable by the Increaſe or wane of the light they pretend unto. To gratify them alſo we ſhall wave the objecting to them, how great a part of the late Troubles of this Nation flowed from their Counſels and Deſignes, and wiſh
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:43664:4"/>that they were buried in an eternal Oblivion, never to riſe up to the reproach of <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> and <hi>Proteſtantiſm,</hi> and not be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred, but to a Caution of being abuſed by the ſame Arts, and of falling again into the like Miſeries.</p>
               <p>The only thing therefore we ſhall take notice of, in this <hi>Plea for Indulgence,</hi> ſhall be to examine the reaſons and arguments they bring to prove, that <q>
                     <hi>All outward violence, and ſeverity upon the account of Diſſenſions.</hi>
                  </q> (For the differences of theſe men from the preſent eſtabliſhment are not bare <hi>Diſſents in Religion,</hi>) <hi>is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute of any firme Foundation in Scripture and Reaſon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Their firſt Argument they will have to be from the <hi>Law of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> which to raiſe a duſt, and amuſe the leſs wary Reader, is drawn out to a needleſs length, and cloathed with an affected obſcurity; for to what purpoſe was it to have been tedious in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving what all grant, that <q>
                     <hi>Every ſingle perſon to prevent mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſchiefs deſtructive to a Community, is to forego his particular conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niences, if they be in things in his own power.</hi>
                  </q> Nor was a long diſcourſe neceſſary to ſhew, that <q>
                     <hi>a Community is not to require of its members, things not in their power,</hi>
                  </q> ſince no ſober man ever dreamt that any thing impoſſible could be the ſubject of a Law.</p>
               <p>But when they aſſume, <q>
                     <hi>That mens Apprehenſions of things Spiritual and ſupernatural, ſuch they mean as have no alliance to the ingrafted light of nature, are not abſolutely in their own power,</hi>
                  </q> &amp; from thence conclude, <q>
                     <hi>that thoſe Apprehenſions and the exerciſes of Conſcience towards God upon them, cannot be the ſubjects of the Laws of civil Societies,</hi>
                  </q> they endeavor to impoſe upon us ſeveral fallacies, particularly theſe two. 1 Their argument ſuppoſes, "<hi>that the Laws are made againſt mens Apprehenſions,</hi> Whereas the Apprehenſions of men are not the ſubject of the Laws, but their Practiſes anſwerable or not anſwerable to the Apprehenſions.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Their Concluſion contains more then was in the Premiſes, for their arguments had only aimed to prove, <q>
                     <hi>that mens Appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions of things Spiritual were not in their power: So that their Diverſity was unavoidable;</hi>
                  </q> but when they conclude, they joyn with theſe apprehenſions the "<hi>Exerciſe of their Conſcience,</hi> of which there was not one word in the premiſes. And as their way of arguing is fallacious, ſo are the propoſitions themſelves not true; for</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:43664:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
1. This propoſition that "<hi>Mens Apprehenſions of things Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual and ſupernatural do not depend on the Liberty of their wills, nor, are in their own power,</hi> As thus crudely propoſed <hi>is falſe.</hi> For all thoſe to whom the Goſpel is preached, if they do not appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend the truth, their not apprehenſion is (1) imputed unto them as their ſin, and wilfull tranſgreſſion; For it is ſaid of them, that <hi>their Hearts were waxed fat, and their Ears are dull of hearing, and their Eyes have they cloſed.</hi> They are ſaid <hi>to reſiſt the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> That <hi>they received not the love of the truth,</hi> &amp;c. But this could not be charged upon them, had it not been in <hi>their power</hi> to apprehend thoſe Spiritual things when preached unto them. (2) They are <hi>puniſhed</hi> for it; for it is ſaid that <hi>God for this cauſe ſent them ſtrong deluſions that they might believe a lye,</hi> and the ſentence of <hi>Damnation</hi> is paſſed upon them, <hi>That they all might be damned who believed not the truth.</hi> But it is injurious to the Divine Goodneſs to ſay that he damns men for that which was notin their Power to avoid. And that he ſhould ſend them ſtrong deluſions to believe a Lye, when it was not in their power to apprehend the Truth. And if it be in the power of men to apprehend the truth, having the Doctrine of Chriſt preached to them, then it is not impoſſible to have the ſame apprehenſions: becauſe the Truth is One and the Same, and varies not in it ſelf, and ſo the Apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions muſt be all the ſame in their nature, <hi>i. e.</hi> in a conformity to the thing apprehended: although there may be difference, as to the degrees. It may be indeed more clear in one then ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, one may apprehend all the parts, ſee further into the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences of things then others: yet ſtill the apprehenſion may be the ſame in eſſence, if men will lay down their prejudices, part with their luſts, repudiate their carnal intereſts, and caſt off the tyranny of cuſtome.</p>
               <p>That which they offer for a proof is full of ambiguity, as if they were afraid to be underſtood; For when they ſay that "<hi>the Will of God in things Supernatural and Spiritual "cannot be known, but by Revelation from himſelf;</hi> We do not know whether they eanm that General Revelation which is made unto us from him the Scriptures, or a Particular Revelation to every ſingle per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: if they mean this latter, they ſhould have proved it. And when they ſay "<hi>that Divine Revelation can not be</hi> 
                  <q>
                     <hi>apprehended or
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:43664:5"/>aſſented unto, but according to the nature and meaſure of that Light which God is pleaſed to communicate unto them, to whom ſuch Revelation is made,</hi>
                  </q> 
                  <hi>We are again at a loſs, for they do not prove that there is a Light different from the Revelation of God; for the truth which God reveals, is the light it ſelf, which like the light of the Sun, makes it ſelf as well as other things to be ſeen. When they ſay</hi> 
                  <q>
                     <hi>this light doth not equally effect the minds of men.</hi> We grant it, but yet we cannot, as they do, deny <hi>that it is poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible it ſhould do ſo:</hi> for although <hi>there be divers wayes and means of Communicating the Truth.</hi>
                  </q> Yet however, God may give to all them to whom the Word is Preached, ſufficient means to Apprehend and acknowledge his Truths. And although <q>
                     <hi>there be different Diſpoſitions of them, to whom the Word is propoſed.</hi>
                  </q> Yet thoſe diſpoſitions whereby men reſiſt, and will not appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend the Truth, are from themſelves, and to their own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, which they may, and ought to lay aſide. So that they have not proved what they intended. And if they had done ſo, yet they would gain nothing by it.</p>
               <p>Becauſe the 2 d. propoſition (which they included in their inference) <hi>The exerciſe of mens conſciences, or the Practices of men upon their apprehenſions of things Spiritual, are not in their power.</hi> Is alſo falſe. <hi>For the practices of Men (which are the Subject of Laws) whether conformable or not to their apprehenſions, are within their pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,</hi> either to act or not act, as ſhall ſeem moſt for the benefit of the Society, the Church. This is plain by that principle of Order which the Apoſtle layes down, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.32. <hi>The Spirits of the Prophets are ſubject to the Prophets,</hi> where by <hi>the Spirits of the Prophets,</hi> the Context ſhews, were ſignified ſome <hi>Inſpirations,</hi> and <hi>gifts</hi> of the Holy Ghoſt as <hi>to Propheſie,</hi> or to <hi>ſing</hi> a <hi>Pſalm,</hi> or <hi>to ſpeak in an unknown Tongue;</hi> and theſe certainly were more vigorous, had a ſtronger impulſe, and more efficacious impreſſions upon the minde of the Prophet, then a bare apprehenſion of a thing could effect: and yet the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>theſe Spirits were ſubject to the Prophets,</hi> whether it were the <hi>Prophets</hi> that received it, ſo that they might forbear, or ſpeak as it ſeemed moſt for Order, and edifying; or elſe to the other <hi>Prophets that were to judge,</hi> ſo that they might give Rules, and Laws for the uſe of thoſe gifts. Of which ſort ſoever you take theſe <hi>Prophets</hi> to be, to whom <hi>the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:43664:6"/>Spirits were to le ſubject,</hi> it argues that it was in their power; and therefore the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> commands that they ſhould uſe it to the benefit of others.</p>
               <p>The ſame is in the Apoſtles counſel, when he directs him that had a particular perſwaſion of the <hi>lawfulneſs</hi> or <hi>unlawfulneſs</hi> of ſome things, to reſtrain that to his own breaſt.
<note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 14.22.</note> 
                  <hi>Haſt thou faith? have it to thy ſelf;</hi> and therefore he was Maſter of his own pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, notwithſtanding his perſwaſion. This the Apoſtle ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes in all theſe admonitions which are given to men of dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent perſwaſions, to preſerve the peace of the Church. For if they were by their perſwaſions to be acted violently, like the <hi>Enthuſiaſts</hi> among the <hi>Idolaters,</hi> that were not able to contain themſelves in their extaſies, it had been in vain to have given counſels to them who were not able to obſerve them. Beſides if God ſhould have concluded us under an <hi>Impoſſibility</hi> of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving all the ſame apprehenſions of Spiritual and ſupernatural things, and bad alſo condemned us all to ſuch a ſlavery to thoſe apprehenſions, as that it ſhould not be in our power to manage our ſelves under them, to the peace and tranquillity of the Church, it had been in effect to have created us to mutual De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions, concluded us under a worſe condition then Brutes, and given us Apprehenſive Faculties only to deſtroy our ſelves and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; all which are contrary to the Divine goodneſs, amd the gentle, meek, and charitable commands of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>But ſay they <q>
                     <hi>To teach men that their conſciences towards God, are not concerned in their not acting according to their Light in his Worſhip, or in acting againſt it, is to teach them to be Atheiſts.</hi>
                  </q> We anſwer, That to teach men not to be over confident in their own apprehenſions, but to be ſo moderate as may be for the Peace of the Church, is not to act contrary to their Conſciences, but moſt agreeably to a well ordered Conſcience; this being a plain, clear, and confeſſed duty by all Chriſtians: the particular apprehenſions of one perſon or party being ſubject to many ſuſpicions, whether they be the right meaſures of a duty or no. And in doing this they are ſo far from being <hi>Atheiſts,</hi> that they become the better <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> following the Rules of Chriſt and his Apoſtles.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:43664:6"/>
               <head>SECT. 3. <hi>Indulgence not juſtified from the Example of Chriſt.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THeir ſecond Argument is drawn from the Example of our Saviour, in which we confeſs we are not only to adore and admire, but alſo to imitate all that Meekneſs, &amp; Lowlyneſs, which rendred his life glorious in holineſs; yet theſe men dare not ſay that the number of our duties is bounded by his example, and that we are to forbear every thing, whereof we have no pattern in his holy Converſation. For then they ſhould not keep <hi>holy the firſt day of the Week,</hi> nor <hi>Baptize Children,</hi> nor <hi>gather particular Congregations,</hi> nor <hi>impoſe Congregational Covenants,</hi> all which theſe men do, and we no where read, that Chriſt did. Beſides, theſe men are not ſo ignorant, as to believe a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative argument to be of any force, though they make uſe of it to commend this doctrine of their intereſt, to the Vulgar; and therefore when they ſay <q>
                     <hi>Coerce, Fine, Impriſon, Baniſh thoſe that apprehend not aright all and every thing that I would have you inſtructed in, are words that never proceeded out of his mouth,</hi> &amp;c.</q> We reply, (1) That this does not inforce, that no Church and State by good Laws, and well proportioned Penalties, ſhould reduce erroneous and diſagreeing Chriſtians to Peace and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. 2. This makes nothing againſt Our Laws, who do not ſay <hi>Coerce, Fine, &amp;c.</hi> thoſe that apprehend not aright all and every thing which Jeſus would have us inſtructed in; for there be many different opinions in the Church of <hi>England</hi> which the Laws of the State and Church take no notice of. And it is not their intent to make men of one minde in all and every thing, (Which yet is to be wiſhed:) But coerce thoſe who do things contrary to the Peace of Chriſtians, and will not ſubmit to their Lawful Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riors, when they command things juſt, and in their power. And this we are ſure may be collected from the words that procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded out of our Saviours mouth.</p>
               <p>Nor is it any more to the purpoſe when they ſay <q>
                     <hi>That it is a marveilous difficulty for any to think ſeriouſly, That he who was ſo full of compaſſion towards all the ſons of men, ſhould ever give the leaſt conſent unto the Puniſhment, and gradual Deſtruction of thoſe
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:43664:7"/>who in ſincerity deſire to Love and Obey them, and do yet unavoidably miſtake in their apprehenſions of ſome few things pleaded to be accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his minde.</hi>
                  </q> For 1. It is our duty, and alſo the duty of all who do pretend to be true Chriſtians, ſeriouſly to think of <hi>thoſe many and very preſſing commands of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that his Diſciples ſhould preſerve unity among themſelves;</hi> and it is our great marvel, that theſe men who pretend ſo high to the name of Chriſt, ſhould yet take no notice of thoſe Precepts.</p>
               <p>Secondly, when we ſeriouſly think of them, we cannot but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, <hi>That theſe Commands of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity preceeded from the fulneſs of his compaſſion towards the Sons of Men.</hi> 1. Towards thoſe men who ſhould deſire to enter into the Kingdom of Heaven; that theſe ſhould not be diſtracted in their choice, what party to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply themſelves unto, with whom they might joyn them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to ſeek the Lord, and where they might moſt aſſuredly receive the Word of Life. Which diſtractions it was not poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for them to avoid, if the Chriſtians were divided into ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral parties. 2. Towards thoſe of the World, who though they would not believe, and ſo ſhould not be concerned in the truth of Chriſtians; yet they muſt be in the Quiet and Peace of them. For experience ſhews, that when Diviſions and Contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons turmoild the Church, the State and even the mixt company of unbelievers ſoon found themſelves under many miſeries, while the contending parties mutually armed to a deſtruction of their Oppoſites.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, <hi>Theſe commands of Chriſt, and this compaſſion to man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde, do oblige every man to endeavour to preſerve that unity by all wayes proper for them in their ſeveral Callings.</hi> And therefore Chriſtian Kings may and ought to do it in their way which is by juſt Laws, and the Church by wiſe and pious Injunctions; and all are to avoid, and mark them that cauſe Diviſions among them, to reſtrain their furious and carnal heats in proſecuting their own private apprehenſions, to the reproach of Religion, and Diſturbance of Mankind.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, <hi>Such wayes to preſerve Peace, can never be to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of thoſe who in ſincerity deſire to Love and obey Chriſt,</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they ſhould miſtake in their apprehenſions of ſome few things, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For (1.) It is not true (which theſe writers ſay)
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:43664:7"/>that ſuch perſons are concluded under "<hi>an unavoidable miſtake;</hi> and being not ſo, they will in ſincerity indeavour after a full and clear information in thoſe things that are pleaded to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the mind of Chriſt. (2.) All ſuch perſons will in that Chriſtian humility which the Spirit of Chriſt works, not oppoſe their private apprehenſions to the judgment and practiſe of that Church of God, from which they have received the Doctrine of Salvation, <hi>and therefore will not think of themſelves above what they ought to think, but think ſoberly according as God hath dealt to them the meaſure of faith.</hi> And being thus lowly in their own eyes knowing themſelves lyable to miſtakes and errors; they will not be ſo fond of their own apprehenſions, as for their ſakes to bring a ſcandal upon the Church of God, and ſet the World in Flames. Beſides, (3.) having a deſire to Obey God, they will be careful to teſtify their obedience in a manifeſt and undeniable Duty, as is the Peace and Unity of Chriſtians, and obedience to Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours: and not think to juſtify the breach of that, with the obſervance of what their ſingular and private apprehenſions re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent; eſpecially being ſecur'd, that the Church from whom they differ, do retain all things neceſſary to ſalvation: as theſe men do profeſs they agree with the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> in all things of that degree. Therefore ſuch perſons are ſecur'd enough from thoſe ſeverities which are neceſſary to preſerve the Peace of a Church and Nation. And ſuch ſincere, humble enquirers after Truth, and thoſe that walk up to what they have already attained, are the only perſons dear to Chriſt. Not every one that cries Lord, Lord; that pretend to preach and prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie in his name; for he himſelf hath told us, that he ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject the pleas of many ſuch to his indulgence. And indeed ſhould every one that is ſo kinde to himſelf, as to publiſh to the World, that he in ſincerity deſires to obey and love Chriſt, be believed upon his own word, and have an indulgence for his differing practiſes, the greateſt Impoſtors that ever appear'd among Chriſtians, muſt be permitted to practiſe their Cheats and Impieties. For the <hi>Gnoſticks,</hi> the <hi>Manichees, Montaniſts, Circumcelliones</hi> of old, and thoſe among us who are yet Red, and polluted with the blood of their Lawful Soveraign, that viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the known Laws of the Land of their nativity, rob'd the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:43664:8"/>Churches, and invaded the juſt rights of every one, within the compaſs of their luſt, and their power. Theſe I ſay would have perſwaded the World, and, it may be, were ſo mad as to believe themſelves, that they were the men that loved Chriſt, when in their works they did deny him. And yet (4.) It cannot be ſaid that the gradual deſtruction, even of theſe men, is intended by ſuch Laws, as do command nothing but what may be for the Security, Peace, and welfare of Chriſtian Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munities: and it is an high ſlander of any Law-givers, to ſay that they intended Puniſhment and not Obedience.</p>
               <p>That inſtance of <q>
                     <hi>Chriſts reproof to his Diſciples, for being ſo forward to call Fire down from Heaven upon the neglectful</hi> Sama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritans,</q> is altogether impertinent; eſpecially as they inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret thoſe words. <hi>You know not of what Spirits you are,</hi> To be <q>
                     <hi>an unacquaintedneſs with their own Spirits, imagining that for Zeal, which was indeed ſelf-Revenge.</hi>
                  </q> So that in their Senſe Chriſt reprov'd their revengeful Spirits. Now it cannot be ſaid of Laws made to reſtrain violations of Peace, that they are the Dictates of Revenge, ſince Revenge looks at acts paſt, but Laws indeavour to prevent thoſe to come.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 4. <hi>No ground for Indulgences in the Practice of the Apoſtles.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe third Argument is drawn from the practice of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, whom we may well wonder, that they ſhould be ſuſpected as Patrons for indulgence of <hi>Diſſentions</hi> and <hi>Schiſms</hi> in Religion; Since we finde them deſcribing the Authors of them, as <hi>Monſters</hi> and <hi>Prodigies,</hi> that diſhonour the Generation they live in, and fill the place wherein they appear with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion and danger, and threaten a Tempeſt at their firſt riſing. Therefore the Apoſtles dealt with them as ſuch in their dayes. For although they did not exerciſe on them <hi>Coertions, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaints,</hi> and <hi>Corporal</hi> puniſhments, as theſe Writers wiſely obſerve; becauſe indeed they had no Temporal power: yet they uſed their <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> power and <hi>delivered them over to Satan,</hi> which in thoſe times was a giving them up to that Tormenter to
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:43664:8"/>be afflicted in their fleſh, a ſeverer puniſhment then the Sword of the Magiſtrate can inflict.
<note place="margin">Rom. 16.18. 1 Tim. 6.4.</note> They commanded the ſound Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians to <hi>avoid</hi> them as contagious Peſts, and to <hi>cut</hi> them off as <hi>cankerd and infeſted</hi> members, that would bring deſtruction to the whole body of the Church, if a juſt ſeverity prevented them not; nay they call'd for Gods aſſiſtance to cut off theſe troublers of the <hi>Iſrael</hi> of God:
<note place="margin">Gal. 5.12.</note> 
                  <hi>I would they were even cut off that trouble you.</hi> They alſo commended nothing more to the converſation of Chriſtians then Peace and Unity, <hi>to minde the ſame things, to walk in one minde, to follow after thoſe things that made for Peace, and Edification,</hi> which are impoſſible to be attained in Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentions. It would be very ſtrange therefore, to imagine, that they who do all this to Diſſentions, ſhould yet give any ground for an Indulgence of them.</p>
               <p>But yet theſe men have found out, <q>that St. <hi>Paul is for this for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearance Phil.</hi> 3.15, 16.</q> Which Text, if they had faithfully ſet down, would have diſcovered their Sophiſtry. For the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Let us therefore as many as be perfect, be thus minded; and if in any thing ye be otherwiſe minded, the Lord ſhall reveal even this unto you. Nevertheleſs whereto we have already attained, let us walk by the ſame rule; let us mind the ſame things.</hi> Here it is plain that thoſe to whom the Apoſtle commends Forbearance one to the other, were thoſe whom he calls perfect; and ſuch cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly could not be perſons that had ſeparated from a mutual Communion, for all ſuch Diviſions he brands as carnal. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. And the Dividers as men not perfect, and at beſt but babes; nay he calls them in the beginning of that very Chapter, <hi>Dogs, Evil workers,</hi> and in ſcorn, the <hi>Conciſion,</hi> and therefore bids them have a care, and beware of them; and in the following verſes weeps over them as <hi>Enemies of the Croſs of Chriſt, whoſe end is deſtruction.</hi> Theſe are not words of forbearance and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence, and therefore that place gives no countenance to it.</p>
               <p>But then they urge, <q>
                     <hi>That the whole Society of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles obſerving the difference between the Jewiſh and Gentile Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers to prevent any Evil Conſequent in their Aſſembly at Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, aſſigned to the ſeveral parties, their particular bounds how far they ſhould accommodate themſelves unto one another by a mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:43664:9"/>Condeſcenſion that they might walk in peace.</hi>
                  </q> What is all this to an indulgence of thoſe who have forſaken the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the Church, and who write, preach, and do all they can againſt it. The Caſe is far unlike. The <hi>differences</hi> between the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> and <hi>Gentile</hi> Beleevers had brought, as yet, no evil Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent, for they themſelves ſay, <q>
                     <hi>the Apoſtles conſulted to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent any evil Conſequent.</hi>
                  </q> Let the world judge whether the Differences among us have not brought upon us a large ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of ſuch Conſequents. The Apoſtles determined, and ſet bounds and meaſures of forbearance to <hi>prevent a Schiſm,</hi> then which nothing was more dreadful to the Church; and theſe men would have forbearance and Indulgence to a <hi>moſt dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous ſchiſme already made,</hi> that ſo it might with impunity be continued.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 5. <hi>The Primitive Chriſtians did not allow Indulgence.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WIth far leſſe ſucceſs, but with more art doe they indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to make the firſt Chriſtians to ſpeak for them, from whom they bring ſome paſſages: yet do not tell us where we alſo may find thoſe Teſtimonies, nor give us the words of the Authors, for fear they ſhould be deprehended. <q>
                     <hi>Socrates</hi> the Hiſtorian (ſay they) <hi>gives us a long Catalogue of differences in External Rites of Worſhip, which they looked upon as no breach of Union at all.</hi>
                  </q>
                  <note place="margin">l. 5. c. 22. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, &amp;c. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, &amp;c.</note> To which we ſay, that That Hiſtorian doth tell us indeed that the Churches of ſeveral Provinces, had different obſervations of the feaſt of <hi>Eaſter,</hi> of the meaſure of Faſts before that Feaſt, and of the different meats they did abſtain from, but ſo that one obſervation was in the whole <hi>Roman</hi> Church, another was kept by thoſe in <hi>Illyrium,</hi> all <hi>Greece</hi> and <hi>Alexandria,</hi> &amp;c. Which we eaſily ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, for we grant to every Church their particular Rites. Our Rites in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> are not preſſ'd upon thoſe in <hi>Scotland,</hi> nor thoſe in <hi>Ireland;</hi> and we do not think our Union with the Proteſtant Churches abroad, is broken by their diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Ceremonies. Therefore the Practice of the firſt Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:43664:9"/>is maintain'd by us and not violated. But they can nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther out of <hi>Socrates</hi> nor any other Hiſtorian of thoſe times give us an inſtance of any one National or Provincial Church, that did indulge thoſe within their juriſdiction who profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Chriſtianity, did yet contemn her Orders, and ſeparate from her Communion, and did declare her Rites in Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, Idolatrous, Superſtitious, and Antichriſtian, which is now our Caſe.</p>
               <p>Then they bring in <q>
                     <hi>Victor Biſhop of Rome is branded for diſturbing the peace of the Churches by dividing their Communion.</hi>
                  </q> They tell us not for what he was cenſured, either becauſe they knew it not, or becauſe they know it would do them no good; The Caſe was this. All the Churches of the leſſer <hi>Aſia</hi> by an ancient Tradition did on the fourteenth day of the Moon obſerve the Feaſt of our Saviours Paſſeover, and upon what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever day of the week that happened to fall, they ended their Faſts. This cuſtom was obſerved in no other Church through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the whole World; for in all the reſt, that cuſtom which was delivered by the Apoſtles, was continued, as <hi>Euſebius</hi> ſaith, to his time. Notwithſtanding this difference, the ſeveral Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches had preſerv'd Peace and Communion; among themſelves, as <hi>Irenaeus</hi> ſaith of <hi>Anicetus, Pius, Hyginus, Teleſphorus, Sixtus,</hi> Biſhops of <hi>Rome,</hi> who had received <hi>Polycarp</hi> and others of the Aſiaticks that came to <hi>Rome,</hi> to Communion not contending a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout that Rite. But afterwards when a controverſie was mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved about it, and both ſides in different Councils decreed for their own practice, and ſent their Letters to juſtifie themſelves to the other Churches.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Euſ.</hi> l. 5. c. 25. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>Victor</hi> heated with the letter of the <hi>Aſiaticks,</hi> without conſulting the other Biſhops of his own Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion, excommunicates all the Churches of <hi>Aſia</hi> as Hetoro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox: <hi>This diſpleaſed all the other Biſhops, who commanded him to conſult the peace and union of the Brethren.</hi> Now what in all this concerns us. <hi>Victor</hi> was to be blamed for breaking a long continued Peace, for invading the Liberty of other Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches; but none would have condemned him, had he requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red obedience from the members of his own Church, to the Orders and Canons made by Councils of thoſe who were over them in the Lord.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:43664:10"/>
For <hi>Irenaeus</hi> in his Epiſtle to <hi>Victor</hi> to diſſwade him from breaking Communion with the Churches of another obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, tells him that his Predeceſſors <hi>Anicetus, Pius,</hi> &amp;c. kept the Communion entire,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jul.</hi> l. 5 c. 26. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> although they did not obſerve thoſe Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches Rites, nor <hi>ſuffered thoſe among them to obſerve them.</hi> And if the infamy of <hi>Victor</hi> is to be a terror to any, it muſt be to thoſe who break the Communion; and it is plain who they are that have done that among us.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Origen</hi> is the next whom they would make the world be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, is for their cauſe; but they are forced to make a teſtimony for him which he himſelf never writ, <hi>viz.</hi> 
                  <q>
                     <hi>That there ever were differences amongſt Profeſſors of Chriſtianity from the beginning; and that it was impoſſible but that there ſhould ſo be, which yet he ſhews, hindred not their Faith, Love, and Obedience.</hi>
                  </q> For when <hi>Celſus</hi> did upbraid and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach the Chriſtians, becauſe of their many Sects, (as <hi>Atheiſts</hi> and <hi>Papiſts</hi> do now to us) <hi>Origen</hi> gives ſome reaſons of them, and then confeſſes indeed that <q>
                     <hi>There were Differences among Chriſtians from their beginning,</hi>
                  </q> but then he doth not ſay what theſe writers ſay for him, <q>
                     <hi>That it was impoſſible but that there ſhould ſo be;</hi>
                  </q> for this would have been to have giuen the lye to the Holy Ghoſt, who in the <hi>Acts c.</hi> 4. <hi>v.</hi> 32. ſaith <hi>That the multitude of them who believed, were of one heart and one ſoul;</hi> and therefore what was then, might be again, and ſo could not be impoſſible. Neither doth <hi>Origen</hi> ſay, much leſs ſhew, that theſe differences, <q>
                     <hi>hindered not their Faith, Love, and Obedience.</hi>
                  </q> For the <hi>Hereſies</hi> which he thought <hi>Celſus</hi> had reſpect unto, and grounded his reproach upon, were the <hi>Ophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tae</hi> and <hi>Cainitae</hi> to whom <hi>Origen</hi> denies the very name of <hi>Chriſtians.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They pretend alſo a kindneſs from <q>
                     <hi>Juſtin Martyr,</hi> who, (they ſay) <hi>in his ſecond Apologie, declares his forbearance and the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of thoſe dayes, towards thoſe who believing in Chriſt, yet thought themſelves obliged to the obſervation of</hi> Moſaical <hi>Rights and Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies.</hi>
                  </q> But this is an open abuſe both of <hi>Juſtin</hi> and the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, for there are no words in that Apology tending to that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, and ſuch indeed would have been impertinent, and beſides his ſubject in that Apology; and laſtly had he ſaid, what he doth not, it would not have been of advantage to Indulgence.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:43664:10"/>
                  <hi>Ignatius</hi> alſo is uſed no better by them, whom they would have to ſay, that <q>
                     <hi>to perſecute men on the account of God and Religion, is to make our ſelves conformable to the Heathen that know not God.</hi>
                  </q> Whereas <hi>Ignatius</hi> ſaith no word like it, but that which makes againſt them.
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ignat. Ep. ad Phila delphinos</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>If any one</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>follows him that hath made a Schiſm, he ſhall not inherit the Kingdom of God. If any one walks in a different opinion, he is not complyant with the ſufferings of Chriſt.</hi> Theſe are the words of <hi>Ignatius,</hi> who in that place by many ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments urges them to continue in the Unity of the Church, and therefore could not at the ſame time ſpeak for indulgence of thoſe who did break that Unity. But thoſe words which they refer to, are the words of the <hi>Interpolator</hi> of <hi>Ignatius.</hi> For they are not in <hi>Voſſius</hi>'s Edition of <hi>Ignatius,</hi> nor in that <hi>Latin</hi> Copy which <hi>Biſhop Uſher</hi> thought to be Authentick: but they are in that corrupt Copy, ſet forth by him; yet ſo ſet forth and noted in <hi>Red</hi> Characters, that no man could take them for <hi>Igna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi>'s, but he that had a mind to prevaricate. Which in civil con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe is an infamous crime, but in Religion we want a name to expreſs its buſeneſs.</p>
               <p>Then they huddle up many witneſſes together, <hi>Tertullian, Origen, Arnobius,</hi> and <hi>Lactantius</hi> 
                  <q>
                     <hi>Who</hi> (ſay they) <hi>pleaded for a Liberty in Religion, as founded in the Law of Nature, and the inconſiſtencie of Faith with Compulſion.</hi>
                  </q> But where theſe Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors ſay ſuch things, they do not tell us; and the former diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veries ſhow how little reaſon we have to take their bare Words. But whatſoever thoſe Authors may ſay to juſtify Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, even by the Law of Nature; and that the light of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon could finde nothing in it that deſerved perſecution: Yet I ſhall not believe, that they ever ſaid,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>de Praeſcrip. Haeret.</hi> c. 37. <hi>Si Haeretici ſunt, Chriſtiani non ſunt. Ib.</hi> c. 32. <hi>Ita om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes Haereſes, nec recipiuntur in pacem &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munionem, ab Eccleſiis quo quo modo Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licis.</hi>
                  </note> the Law of Nature did give to any perſons ground for Liberty of different Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, and practiſes, contrary to the Rules and Orders of that Chriſtian Church, wherein they lived, until I ſee their own words for it. And of theſe certainly <hi>Tertullian</hi> can have no great favour for them, who is ſo ſevere againſt <hi>Hereticks</hi> in his Book <hi>de Praeſcriptione,</hi> that he will not allow them the name of <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> and ſaith, <hi>that they were not received to peace and Communion in the Churches that were any way Apoſtolical.</hi> If therefore we may judge of the reſt by one, we have no reaſon to think they are for the the <hi>Indulgence,</hi> till we ſee it under their hands.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:43664:11"/>
After theſe they bring the <q>
                     <hi>Synod of</hi> Alexandria <hi>in the Caſe of</hi> Athanaſius, <hi>who did (as they ſay), Condemn all External force in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and Reproached the</hi> Arians <hi>as the firſt Inventers, and Promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of it.</hi>
                  </q> The ſhamefulneſs of this Allegation will appear to the Reader; If he take notice, that this <hi>Synod,</hi> made no Acts nor Canons, for the Hiſtories of it mention none, nor are any Extant; and therefore their Judgment in this Caſe was not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitive. Their main buſineſs was to inquire into the Sclanders which the <hi>Arians</hi> had raiſed againſt <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> and to bear witneſs againſt them, they being competent to this, as being Members of the ſame Church, and converſant with him in his offices. This their Teſtimony they publiſhed in a <hi>Circulatory Letter</hi> to all the Biſhops of the <hi>Catholick</hi> Church, and to their beloved Brethren in Chriſt. In this Epiſtle they ſpeak not at all concerning <hi>Exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal force in Religion,</hi> nor do they ſay the <hi>Arians</hi> were the firſt inventers of it. For they only complain of the <hi>Arians</hi> for offering to the Emperour, Letters that did accuſe
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Siquidem jam denuo Accuſatrices Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teras contra</hi> Athanaſium <hi>Imperatoribus por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rexere, iteratis calumniis homicidia ei objicientes quae aunquam facta ſunt; ac denuo illum conjurationibus ſuis opprime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re ſtudent.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Athanaſius</hi> of <hi>Murders which were never done, that by that means they might take away his life by the Sword of Juſtice.</hi> And as to this, not to any force of the <hi>Emperour</hi> about Religion, they ſay,
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Tota enim eorum accuſatrix Epiſtola nihil aliud niſi necem ſpectat, aut necem moliuntur ſi ipſis liceat, aut ſaltem exules facere,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Iſta opera Ethnicorum ſunt, &amp; non vel tenuiter Chriſtianorum, &amp; minime omnium Epiſcoporum, quos aliis juſtitiam commonſtrare oportuit.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Their whole Libel deſignes nothing elſe but ſlaughter, as much as in them lies, or elſe baniſhment,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Thoſe are works of</hi> Heathens, <hi>and not of the meaneſt Chriſtians, much leſs of Biſhops, whom it becomes to be patterns of Juſtice to others.</hi> Now what is all this which is ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of bloody Slanders, to the force which reſtrains different Apprehenſions from diſturbing Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. Let the Reader ſee if he can, for I cannot, finde any thing to their purpoſe in that <hi>Synodical</hi> Epiſtle; and if theſe Writers had intended ſincerity, they would have given us the very words which made for them, and I conceive they did not, becauſe they could not. Thus of theſe Teſtimonies out of that ancient Chriſtians, ſome are meer Fictions, the alledged Authors having no ſuch words as theſe are cited to have. Thus <hi>Juſtin Martyr, Origen, Ignatius,</hi> and the <hi>Synod</hi> of <hi>Alexandria</hi> are abuſed. <hi>Tertul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:43664:11"/>Arnobius, Lactantius,</hi> brought in as Witneſſes without any Teſtimony. <hi>Socrates</hi> the Hiſtorian, and the Inſtance of <hi>Victor</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinently mention'd. Truth ſtands not in need of ſuch low ſhifts.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 6. <hi>The firſt Chriſtian Emperours were againſt Indulgence.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HAving done with Churchmen, They come to Emperours. And firſt they lay hold of that Edict of <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> who having a mind to deliver the oppreſſed <hi>Chriſtians</hi> from the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and not finding it ſafe,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Euſeb. Hiſt.</hi> l. 10. c. 5.</note> as yet to appear particularly in their favour, having then <hi>Licinius</hi> and <hi>Maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minus</hi> Collegues in the Empire, both ſtill enclined to <hi>Gentiliſm,</hi> He prevails upon <hi>Licinius</hi> to joyn with him in this Publick E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict, <hi>That Liberty of Worſhip was not to be denied to any; and that it ſhould be permitted to every mans will to embrace what Rites and Inſtitutes of Religion they pleaſed; and that the Chriſtians as well as all others might obſerve the Faith of their own Religion.</hi> But when he found that this did not fully ſecure the Chriſtians, and it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing general, as alſo ambiguous, ſo that for all this, many of them for fear did deny the faith. When they came to <hi>Milan,</hi> they did make another Explanatorie Edict, more fully in the favour of the Chriſtians, That <hi>the Liberty of Embracing the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion of Chriſtians ſhould be denied to no man.</hi> Now let any reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable men judge what they can gain for their Cauſe, from this Edict, which only gives a liberty to <hi>Chriſtians</hi> in General, as well as to <hi>Idolaters,</hi> and ſpeaks nothing of any Sects and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters among the Chriſtians. But <hi>they ſay,</hi> 
                  <q>
                     <hi>until the latter end of his Reign, there were no thoughts of exerciſing Severity, with refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence unto any Diviſions among Chriſtians about the Worſhip of God.</hi>
                  </q> Where they will fix the Epocha of the end of his Reign, they do not tell us; but this we are certain of, from the beſt Authors, that having not made his Edict for the <hi>Liberty of Chriſtians in gene. ral,</hi> till the 8<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> year of his Reign;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aug. Cont. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt. Parm.</hi> l. c. 7.</note> and ſo publickly owned their Profeſſion: He did in his 11<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> year, and not long after the firſt Councel of <hi>Arles,</hi> make ſevere Edicts. For <hi>Parmenianus</hi> the <hi>Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt</hi> complained that <hi>Conſtantine commanded thoſe of that Sect, to be led forth to Puniſhment.</hi> They were alſo <hi>baniſhed</hi> by him, about the ſame time. For in the <hi>Conference</hi> at <hi>Carthage,</hi> they urged the Letters of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> to <hi>Verinus,</hi> otherwiſe <hi>Valerius</hi> the Prefect
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:43664:12"/>of <hi>Africa,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aug. Brevic. Collat.</hi> 31. <hi>Diei c.</hi> 5.</note> that he ſhould <hi>free them from Baniſhment, and leave their fury to the Judgment of God;</hi> Which Letters St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith, were dated four years and ſix moneths, after the decree of <hi>Baniſhment:</hi> 30. <hi>Non. Maj. Criſpus</hi> and <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> being the ſecond time Conſuls. And therefore <hi>Conſtantine</hi> had dealt ſeverely in ſuch caſes, in the eleventh year of his Reign, which was long before the end of it;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aug. Cent. Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teras Petil.</hi> l. 2. c. 92.</note> for it laſted about 32 years. Beſides, <hi>Conſtantine</hi> took from them about this time, thoſe Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, which by their flattery of <hi>Julian,</hi> they afterwards reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered; by all which it appears, theſe Gentlemen are fouly miſtaken in the forbearance of <hi>Conſtantine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They erre as groſſely when they ſay, that <q>
                     <hi>After the riſe of the Arian Hereſie, when the Interpoſition of Civil cenſures upon the account of Difference about things Spiritual, had made an entrance, by the Sollicitations of ſome for the Baniſhment of</hi> Arius, <hi>and ſome of his Copartners, it is not eaſie to relate what miſeries and Confuſions were brought upon the Churches thereby,</hi>
                  </q> &amp;c. For this is contradictory to their own teſtimony which they brought from the <hi>Syned</hi> of <hi>Alexand;</hi> whom they will have to reproach the <hi>Arians</hi> as the firſt Inventers of external force: and now they will have the Orthodox make an entrance for it, (which in common ſenſe is to begin it) for they were the zealous Solli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citors for the Baniſhment of <hi>Arius.</hi> But as that was a falſe Teſtimony; ſo this is a falſe remark on the Hiſtories of thoſe times. For if by <hi>External Force</hi> they mean the <hi>Uſe of the Civil Power, to remove men of different apprehenſions from their Offices and the Emoluments of the Church,</hi> this was uſed by Chriſtians long before the <hi>Arian</hi> Hereſie aroſe, or the <hi>Emperours</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came Chriſtians. For when <hi>Paulus Samoſatenus</hi> was condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for an <hi>Heretick</hi> by a ſecond <hi>Synod</hi> at <hi>Antioch,</hi> and depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed from his Biſhoprick, yet refuſing to deliver up the Biſhops Houſe that belonged to that Church, they craved aid from the Emperour <hi>Aurelianns</hi> an Heathen. Who commanded <hi>that poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion ſhould be given to him, to whom the Biſhops of</hi> Italy <hi>and</hi> Rome <hi>ſhould determine,</hi> and ſo ſaith <hi>Euſebius, Paulus Samoſate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus was with great diſgrace turned out by the ſecular Power.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Euſeb.</hi> l. 7. c. 30.</note> To no other end was the Civil Power ſollicited in the Caſe of <hi>Arius.</hi> For after all means uſed to reclaim the Hereticks, by
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:43664:12"/>private Admonition, by <hi>Provincial Councils,</hi> by <hi>Exhortatory</hi> Letters from the <hi>Emperour</hi> to peace and Unity; yet Ambition, Vanity, and Opiniaſtrete ſtill propagated the Error, to the ſhame of Religion, the diſquiet of the World, the grief of that Chriſtian Prince, and his Obſtruction to noble deſigns. The Emperour is ſollicited to call that Famous Council of <hi>Nice,</hi> wherein <hi>Arius</hi> his Hereſie was condemned, and a Creed compoſed to which all ſubſcribed at firſt, except five. Who not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding afterwards did in a Petition preſent their recanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and ſubſcribed to the Creed, ſo that the Catholick Faith was agreed to by all: and all ſubſcribed to the Condemnation of the Hereſie, as alſo to the <hi>Anathema</hi> of the Heretick, except <hi>Euſebius</hi> of <hi>Nicomedia</hi> and <hi>Theognis</hi> of <hi>Nice,</hi> who thereupon were by the Council condemn'd and deprived of their Sees, and others ſubſtituted in their places. <hi>Conſtantine</hi> interpoſing nothing herein, but putting the Decree of the Council in Execution, and expelling theſe men from thoſe places where they might diſturbe the peace of the Church. Yet afterwards theſe perſons upon their ſubmiſſion were reſtored again to their Churches. This was all the External force which the Orthodox Chriſtians made uſe of, in which no Sect can find any thing blameable, ſince they all have, and will ſtill, uſe the ſame in their ſeaſons.</p>
               <p>But if by <hi>External Force</hi> they mean the violencies of Fire and Sword, and all thoſe tortures and rigors, which enemies mutually uſe one againſt another: this the orthodox gave no entrance to, but the <hi>Arians</hi> did firſt practice it, and did go beyond all pattern and provocation from the <hi>Catholicks.</hi> For theſe only ſecured the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick peace, againſt ſuch who were in ſome lawful Synod con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn'd as corrupters of that Faith once delivered to the Saints: by depriving them of their Offices in the Church, removing them from thoſe places of their Converſation, where they might either corrupt others, or make a publick di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbance, and reſtraining their Conventicles and meetings. Now this could not juſtifie the <hi>Arians,</hi> who beyond all this, having prevailed with <hi>Conſtantius</hi> to embrace their Hereſie, did put a force upon Councils to determine what they pleaſed, as the <hi>Council</hi> of <hi>Arles,</hi> the <hi>Council</hi> of <hi>Milan,</hi> and <hi>Byterris:</hi> in
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:43664:13"/>which having refuſed to admit an enquiry into the <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Doctrine</hi> of <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> and <hi>denying</hi> to ſubſcribe to the <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cene Creed:</hi> they would notwithſtanding force the Orthodox to ſubſcribe to his condemnation againſt common reaſon. And upon this account they baniſhed <hi>Liberius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome, Oſius,</hi> and <hi>Paulinus,</hi> the moſt eminent Biſhops of the World. Beſides the cruelties they committed at <hi>Alexandria,</hi> and branding Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men with the marks of thoſe condemned to the Mines: they ſent out their Notaries to force both Biſhops and people to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe, upon the pain of Plundering, Impriſonment, and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick ſhames. So that <hi>Hilarie</hi> ſaith, the <hi>Emperours war againſt</hi> Perſia <hi>was ſhorter then that againſt</hi> Alexandria, where the Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elties of the Heathen Perſecutors were acted over again. This was the External force of the <hi>Ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ns,</hi> for which the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks gave them no precedent. And this was that force for which <hi>Hilarius</hi> writ both to, and againſt <hi>Conſtantius.</hi> For he wrote after the Council of <hi>Milan,</hi> and was baniſhed in that of <hi>Byterris.</hi> And therefore his words to <hi>Conſtantius</hi> concern not our Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates who uſe not his Cruelties, but condemn his practices. Theſe doing no more then what Orthodox Princes have done ever ſince there were ſuch in the Church. Beſides, I muſt mind the Reader that the words of S. <hi>Hilarie</hi> cited by theſe Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, are not a continued part of <hi>Hilaries</hi> diſcourſe, but a Rhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſodie out of ſeveral places, which if conſidered with the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text, will appear not to ſerve the ends they were brought for.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Valens</hi> his cruelty was no more juſtifiable by any practices of the Catholicks, then that of <hi>Conſtantius</hi> could be. <hi>Arianiſm</hi> found his nature cruel, and did, as all Hereſies, inflame him higher to a more importunate thirſt for blood, and direct all his ſavage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs againſt the <hi>Orthodox.</hi> But theſe Gentlemen are miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly out, when they ſay <q>
                     <hi>Themiſtius the Philoſopher upon the principles of Common Reaſon and Honeſty plainly told Valens, That by the way he uſed, he might force ſome to venerate his Imperial Robes,</hi>
                  </q> 
                  <hi>but never any to worſhip God aright.</hi> For this was not ſpoken to <hi>Valens,</hi> but in a Conſular ſpeech to <hi>Jovian,</hi> to whom <hi>Valens</hi> ſucceeded. And that not to reſtrain his Cruelty, but to extol that Prince, as being aboue all the arts of Flatterers; in
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:43664:13"/>that he told the ſeveral parties of Chriſtians (whom <hi>Themiſtius</hi> meant by flatterers) making their firſt addreſſes to him when he was <hi>Emp rour. That he would trouble none of what Faith ſoever, but he would have the greateſt kindneſs for thoſe who ſhould endeavour moſt for the Unity of the Church;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Soc. Eccl. Hiſt.</hi> l. 3. c. 25.</note> And the obſervation of <hi>Themiſtius</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon was not grounded on the Principles of Common Reaſon and Honeſty: but was a meer Scoff and Jeer, (ſo much contempt doth Diſſentions expoſe Chriſtianity unto) for his Words are, <hi>They worſhipped not God, but the Emperial Robe; and they were like an Eddie or Whirlpoole, that was hurried one while this way, another that.</hi> It is true indeed, <hi>Themiſtius</hi> laboured to reſtrain the cruelty of <hi>Valens</hi> towards all, as well as towards Chriſtians, even in the beginning of his Reign; and he made the ſame attempt towards the latter end of it, adviſing him,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Socr. Heſt.</hi> l. 4. c. 32. <hi>Sozom.</hi> l. c. 36.</note> 
                  <hi>That he ſhould not perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute the Orthodox Chriſtians, becauſe they differed from him.</hi> And that by this Argument, <hi>That he ought not to wonder at the Diſſentions in Church-mens Opinions; becauſe it was much leſs then that which was among the Gentiles, with whom there were above</hi> 300 <hi>different Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, and from ſuch a multitude there muſt neceſſarily ariſe very many Contentions; and perchance it ſeemed fit to God, that it ſhould be ſo; for when he would not eaſily be known, every one would the more reverence him, becauſe they could not exactly comprehend him.</hi> But I think this argument would not do well in the mouth of a Chriſtian; Howſoever, this prevailed not upon him, wholly to forbear his Cruelty, though it ſomewhat allayed it; for he ſtill was Barbarous to the Orthodox <hi>Clergie,</hi> and it was the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles of his Empire, that hindred the further Executions of his Wrath on them.</p>
               <p>There is no more truth in what they ſay next <q>
                     <hi>But the beſt Emperours in the mean time bewailed thoſe fierce Animoſities, whereby every Sect and Party laboured to oppreſs their Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and kept themſelves from putting forth their Authority againſt any Diſſenters in Chriſtian Religion, who retained the Foundation of the Faith in any Competent meaſure.</hi>
                  </q>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cod. Theodoſian</hi> 16. <hi>Tit.</hi> 5. <hi>Edit. Lugd.</hi> 1664.</note> For let the Reader but look in the <hi>Code of Theodoſius.</hi> and he ſhall finde that there are no leſs then <hi>ſixty two</hi> Laws made againſt <hi>Hereticks</hi> and <hi>Schiſmaticks;</hi> and that of all the <hi>Emperours</hi> from <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great to <hi>Valentinian</hi> the Third, except, <hi>Julian</hi> the Apoſtate, (who
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:43664:14"/>ſought by a Toleration to ruin Chriſtianity) <hi>Conſtantius</hi> and <hi>Valens,</hi> who were reputed Hereticks, and made Laws againſt the Catholick Chriſtians. And theſe Laws were not only a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſuch Hereticks as deſtroyed the <hi>Foundation of the Faith:</hi> but thoſe alſo who, <hi>in a competent meaſure did retain it,</hi> as the <hi>Aeriani, Audiani, Novatiani, Euchitae,</hi> and ſeveral of the ſame Nature; And beſides theſe 62 Laws againſt Hereticks in general, There are <hi>Severall Laws</hi> againſt thoſe that did <hi>Rebaptize.</hi> How ſecure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly therefore, (not to ſay unfaithfully) do theſe men ſay, that "<hi>the beſt Emperours did not put forth their Authority againſt Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters in Religion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But they ſay, <q>
                     <hi>Valentinianus by publick Decree, granted Liberty of Religion unto all Chriſtians.</hi>
                  </q> 
                  <hi>For which they cite Sozomen,</hi> and <hi>Ammianus Marcellinus.</hi> But this is ſaid by neither. For <hi>Sozo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, l.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 6. (And the Adverſaries tell us not any other place, there we ſhould finde this Teſtimony) Saith only this, <hi>He was of the ſame Opinion with thoſe of the Council of</hi> Nice, <hi>and theſe he did benefit, and to thoſe that were otherwiſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, he gave no trouble.</hi> Here is no mention of a Publick decree. Neither doth <hi>Ammianus</hi> ſpeak of any ſuch thing,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Amm. Marc.</hi> l. 30. <hi>Inter Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onum diverſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes medius ſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tit, nec quem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam inquieta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit.</hi>
                  </note> but among the other Characters he gives <hi>that Prince</hi> at his Death, he deſcribes his Moderation. <hi>That he unconcerned himſelf in the differences of Religion, nor did he diſquiet any,</hi> &amp;c. This of <hi>Ammianus, a Gentile,</hi> is to be underſtood of <hi>Valentinian</hi>'s Toleration of <hi>Gentiliſm,</hi> which having been ſo much revived and careſſed by <hi>Julian,</hi> was not preſently to be depreſſed, leſt it might burden the beginnings of his Empire, with too great difficulties. Beſides, by ſuch a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral permiſſion for a time he ſhould more ſafely deliver Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity from the Injuries the <hi>Apoſtate</hi> had done unto it. But I cannot ſee what reaſon theſe Proteſtants have to boaſt in a Toleration, that gives equal Priviledges to <hi>Idolaters,</hi> or <hi>Atheiſts,</hi> as them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. As to that which <hi>Sozomen</hi> ſaith, that he gave no trouble to thoſe that were otherwiſe perſwaded it was in the beginning of his Empire alſo: for that he did not perſevere in that Humor, appears by the ſeveral Laws, he made againſt <hi>Hereticks</hi> and <hi>Schiſmaticks.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d. Th.</hi> l. 16. <hi>Tit.</hi> 5. l. 13.</note> That againſt the <hi>Manichees,</hi> for he commanded that <hi>whereſoever the meetings and company of</hi> Manichees <hi>ſhould be, their Teachers being cenſured, the Houſe and dwelling, where they were taught, ſhould be confiſcated</hi> in the <hi>ninth year</hi> of his Reign,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:43664:14"/>and in the <hi>tenth</hi> he made another againſt <hi>Rebaptizing;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">(2) <hi>Ib. Ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> 6. <hi>Lex prima.</hi>
                  </note> Beſides his <hi>Reſcript</hi> to <hi>Olybrius,</hi> that <hi>he ſhould forbid the Diſſenters at</hi> Rome, <hi>to meet within twenty miles of</hi> Rome, And that to <hi>Praetextatus,</hi> whereby he commanded to baniſh <hi>Urſicinus:</hi> So that this, one of the Beſt Emperours did put forth his Authority againſt Diſſenters in Religion.</p>
               <p>The next they name is <hi>Gratianus,</hi> who they ſay made a Law, that <hi>Religion ſhould be free to all ſorts and Sects of Chriſtians, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the</hi> Manichees, Photinians, <hi>and</hi> Eunomian. This inſtance makes againſt themſelves; for their reaſons which they uſe for ſorbearance, will make as well for Indulgence to the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nichees, Photinians,</hi> and <hi>Eunomians;</hi> becauſe their apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are not in their own power. Chriſt did not bid Coerce, nor <hi>baniſh</hi> thoſe Sects; and the Apoſtles ſpoke nothing of them, nor againſt them: and yet they produce <hi>Gratian</hi> for one of the beſt Emperours that did except them from all Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gency. And indeed, he did not only except theſe,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cod.</hi> 16. <hi>Tit.</hi> 5. l. 4, 5. <hi>Olim (pro Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gione Catholicae Sanctitatis, ut Coetus hareilcae uſurpationis quieſcerent) juſſimus, ſive in oppidis ſive in agris extra Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſias quas no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtra Pax obtinet conventus age<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentur, publica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri loca omnia in quibus falſo Religionis ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentu altaria locarentur, Quod ſive diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimulatione Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicum, ſeu Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fanorum Impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitate, eadem erit ex utroque pernicies. Cod.</hi> 16. <hi>Tit.</hi> 5. l. 5.</note> but he made three Laws againſt the Conventicles of all other Hereticks. Two of theſe Laws are in <hi>Codex Theodoſianus;</hi> The firſt there ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt doth imply a Law made before againſt them; For theſe are the Words <hi>We have heretofore commanded for the good of the Holy Catholick</hi> Religion, that the <hi>Aſſemblies of the Heretical Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation ſhould ceaſe. Whether theſe meetings were held either in Towns, or in the Countries, without thoſe Churches which are of our Communion; all thoſe places to be returned into our Exchequer, in which by a falſe pretence of Religion, Altars were placed, which if it ſhould happen</hi> (to be neglected) <hi>either by the Connivence of the Judges, or by perverſeneſs of the profane</hi> (Hereticks) <hi>there ſhall be the ſame puniſhment for either cauſe.</hi> Here is a Law implied, which is confirmed by this, and that Law is proved to be made by <hi>Gratian,</hi> about the end of 375 year of our Lord, in which his Father being dead, he was Supreme in the Weſtern Empire; and the Law here ſet forth, was about the year 378. While <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lens</hi> was yet alive. But after the death of <hi>Valens,</hi> he going in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>Eaſtern Empire,</hi> and finding the Corruptions there very high, he was neceſſitated to Temporize, and there at <hi>Sirmium</hi> he made that Conſtitution which <hi>Socrates</hi> and <hi>Sozomen</hi> ſpeak of, <hi>of granting Liberty to all but the</hi> Manichees, Photinians, <hi>and</hi> Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomians.
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:43664:15"/>But he was not long in that minde, for he revers'd that, and made another <hi>Law againſt all Hereticks;</hi> which is the fift Law againſt Hereticks, in <hi>Cod. Theod.</hi> Thus it appears that this other beſt Emperour <hi>Gratianus</hi> did put forth his Authority againſt Diſſenters in Religion; and they have not found any one among thoſe ancient Chriſtian Emperours, that hath been for their Indulgence, but againſt it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 7. <hi>Indulgence not to be grounded upon the practice of the Modern Emperours and Princes.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BUt the Apologiſts having been abuſed themſelves, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring to abuſe us with an Opinion, that the Beſt Ancient Emperours were for Indulgence, with ſtrange ill luck, or a Monſtrous inadvertencie ſay, <hi>They</hi> (<hi>i. e.</hi> Ancient Emperours) <hi>have not been without their followers in thoſe Ages, wherein the Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences about Religion have riſen to as great an height, as they are capable of, &amp;c.</hi> And the following Princes whom they name are <hi>Popiſh</hi> Emperours, ſome of whom, they themſelves brand with Perfidiouſneſs and cruelty, as <hi>Sigiſmund</hi> and <hi>Charles the Fifth,</hi> and of the others <hi>Ferdinand, Maximilian, Rodolphus;</hi> they bring no clear Teſtimonies, that they did grant Liberty to all, and every Religion: or that they did abate the Cruelty and Rigour of the Laws that were made by their Predeceſſors, and were ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by the Popes, againſt Diſſenters in Religion. So that they urge theſe great names only to amuſe the unacquainted Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der: which judicious men will plainly ſee, are Witneſſes, either that ſignify nothing, or elſe againſt them.</p>
               <p>As for the blot upon <hi>Sigiſmund</hi>'s <hi>Honour, in breaking his Word of Safety and Liberty to</hi> John Huſs, and <hi>Jerome</hi> of <hi>Prague,</hi> it can no whit ſtain thoſe Princes, who by publick Laws do openly forewarn their Subjects of falling into danger, and do not ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe them by any falſe, and baſe Practices.</p>
               <p>Nor are we more concerned in the Events of <hi>Charles, the Fifth's filling the World with Blood and Uprores, for the Extirpati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Proteſtantiſm.</hi> Since our Laws are not writ in Blood as
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:43664:15"/>his was. Is there no difference betwixt an Emperours In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſions upon Free Princes, and Cities, and a Kings and Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments giving Laws to their own People? Suppoſe he were un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy in the uſe of Power beyond the limits of Juſtice, is it not therefore Lawful to uſe a Power within its due bounds? But how can theſe Writers apply his Loſſes and Diſappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments towards his latter end, as the iſſue of his deſignes againſt <hi>Proteſtantiſm?</hi> How do they know, (as they uſed to ſay) the minde of God in that Providence; Since as great perſecutors of the truth, as he was, went to their Graves in outward Peace and glory. They cannot gather it from the Inſtruments of his Loſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and Diſappointments. For <hi>Maurice</hi> of <hi>Saxony</hi> had been one, though a Proteſtant, who had aſſiſted him in his War upon the other Proteſtants, and had received as a reward of his ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, the Dominions and Electorſhip of <hi>John Frederick</hi> Duke of <hi>Saxony,</hi> his kinſman; and this man did rather ſurprize him, then deal as a Generous Enemy. <hi>Charles</hi>'s greateſt Loſſes, was from <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>ſecond</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> a man more greedy of Proteſtants blood, then <hi>Charles</hi> had appeared to be. Laſtly, His loſs were ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied, by ſome <hi>Jeſuites</hi> to his Injuries to Pope <hi>Clement</hi> the <hi>eighth,</hi> whom by his Armies he beſieged in St. <hi>Angelo.</hi> So little ground have men to fix the Providences of God upon what they diſlike. That they are caſually aplyed to contra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> with equal probability.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Ferdinand</hi> (they ſay) <hi>his Brother and Succeſſor, kept the Peace of the Empire, by a conſtant Peace, granted to the Conſciences of Men.</hi>
                  </q> They ſhould have proved this by ſome Authentick Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory, for <hi>Sleidan</hi> tells us he was not very Indulgent to the Poor <hi>Bohemians:</hi> But they neither ſhew us how, and when he changed his minde; and when he gave an Indulgence, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſed his Brothers decrees. <hi>Maximilian's</hi> ſaying (which they do not tell us from whom they learned it) <hi>i. e. That the Empire of Conſcience belonged to God alone, wherein he would never interpoſe,</hi> Signifies nothing, unleſs his practice were agreeable to it, which they do not aſſert. His Counſel to <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>Third</hi> of <hi>France</hi> returning out of <hi>Poland,</hi> was,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Thuani Hiſt.</hi> l. 58.</note> (as <hi>Thuanus</hi> ſaith) <hi>That in the beginnings of his Reign, and firſt entrance to</hi> France, <hi>he ſhould eſtabliſh Peace;</hi> for ſo ſaid he, <hi>the dreadfull memory of the paſt actions, would be aboliſhed, and the Blame of them would be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:43664:16"/>rather to others then him.</hi> This amounts to no more then an <hi>Act of Oblivion,</hi> which yet we ſee among us, doth not ſettle our Peace. Or if it be to be underſtood of a Peace, as to Religion, it may be underſtood of a Forbearance, as to thoſe Acts of Blood, which <hi>Henry</hi> had been guilty of; for he was one of the prime Actors in the great <hi>French Maſſacre</hi> of Proteſtants. For there we finde no Words of <hi>Maxmilian,</hi> that ſignify granting an Indulgence to all Religions.</p>
               <p>Neither do we finde what they ſay of the ſame <hi>Henry the third,</hi> 
                  <q>
                     <hi>that he left it as his laſt Advice to his Counſellors; that they ſhould no more with Force interpoſe in the matters of Religion.</hi>
                  </q> For <hi>Thuanus</hi> an Hiſtorian of unqueſtionable Credit,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Thuan. Hiſt.</hi> l. 96.</note> gives us his laſt Speech to his Counſellors, after he had been ſtab'd by <hi>Clement</hi> the Friar; in which there is not one word to that purpoſe. All that he ſaith is this, that the Cauſe of Religion ſhould not terrify them from accepting <hi>Henry</hi> of <hi>Navarre</hi> to be their King, who had a right to be ſo;
<note place="margin">Ib. Proteſtantes irreconciliabili odio uſque ad Ultimum Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum proſecutus eſt.</note> and in the Characters of this Prince, <hi>Thuanus</hi> ſaith, <hi>that he Proſecuted the Proteſtants with an irreconciliable ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred to his laſt End.</hi> How miſerably are theſe Apologiſts put to it, to finde Friends for their Cauſe, when they are forced to pretend to a Kindneſs, that never was, from ſuch an Enemy of Proteſtants as this was.</p>
               <p>They do not tell us from what good Author they received the <hi>ſaying</hi> of <hi>Rodolphus</hi> the <hi>Emperour upon the defeat of his Forces. That he looked for no other Iſſue, ſince he invaded the Throne of God, by impoſing on the Conſciences of Men.</hi> But ſuppoſe it true, he might juſtly expect it, if he broke his Faith given to the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants before, or unjuſtly took from them the Peace his Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors had granted; And yet this is nothing at all to prove a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of Indulgence to thoſe various Diſſenters, to whom the Laws alwaies have denied it, and no Prince of ours ever gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to them, and who only had forced impunity to themſelves, by an unjuſt Arms.</p>
               <p>We condemn, as well as they, the Butcheries of the Duke of <hi>Alva:</hi> But we think the Toleration granted by <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>fourth,</hi> can be no precedent for Indulgence to them; The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants in <hi>France</hi> had their Toleration granted long before, and were unjuſtly uſed in the breaking of their Peace. <hi>Henry</hi> the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:43664:16"/>
                  <hi>Fourth</hi> therefore reſtores them what was their own: and it had been ſtrange if he ſhould not, for he was obliged to it, by all the ties of Gratitude. He had been bred up in the ſame Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, they had been his Support in all his Dangers, and were a Conſiderable part of his Strength againſt the <hi>Holy League.</hi> Let but the merits of our Diſſenters to the Crown, be weighed with thoſe; and if they can poſſibly appear equal, let them have what they deſerve.</p>
               <p>Theſe are the <hi>Wiſe</hi> and <hi>Mighty Monarchs,</hi> whoſe practices they appeal unto, theſe are thoſe that were followers of the Beſt Ancient Emperours; And yet none of theſe make any thing for them. It is a wonder that they could finde no Proteſtant Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to be their Patrons, but they muſt be only for the Popiſh. It might have been expected, that among the Beſt, Mighty, and Wiſe Monarchs we ſhould have found <hi>Edward</hi> the <hi>ſixt,</hi> Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and King <hi>James;</hi> who by the confeſſion of all ſound Proteſtants, deſerved well of their Profeſſion: But theſe are left out of their Catalogue of beſt Princes, becauſe theſe were not for their Indulgence. They conclude with an empty boaſt; "<hi>The World is full of Inſtances of the like kinde,</hi> which we cannot believe; for ſure in ſuch a multitude they might have found ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more leſs impertinent then thoſe they bring, or elſe they have no good judgment in their Choice: but ſuch a confident boaſt was neceſſary to hide their real want.</p>
               <p>Thus having examined their reaſons, and Inſtances for In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence, I think it unneceſſary to reflect upon their <hi>Corolla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries Harangues,</hi> and their other obſervations; for their grounds being founde falſe, and naught, all their ſuperſtuctures will fall of themſelves. Neither do I envy them the prayſes they make for themſelves, (the greateſt arguments they uſe to the People;) and therefore ſhall not contradict them: my deſigne being only to ſearch for the truth, which I deſire they may imbrace, and no longer ſeek to perpetuate their Schiſms, to the unſpeakable Diſhonour of Chriſtianity.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:43664:17"/>
               <head>SECT. 8. <hi>A Vindication of the Diſcourſe of Toleration, from the Exceptions in the Second Diſcourſe of Religion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HAving confirmed the <hi>Diſcourſe of Toleration</hi> againſt thoſe Arguments that are for Indulgence, It is requiſite to ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtify it alſo againſt the Exceptions that are made againſt it in <hi>the ſecond Diſcourſe of Religion,</hi> whoſe Title boaſts an <hi>Anſwer</hi> to it, but the following Treatiſe ſhews how frontleſs the Title Page is. For he hath not conſidered at all, thoſe grounds upon which Toleration is unjuſtifiable, nor thoſe reaſons which ſhow it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Intereſt of this Nation; but rather indeavouring to delude his Reader then anſwer his Adverſary, he hath ſelected only ſome few paſſages for the Subjects of his Contradiction, with out conſidering that order and method, in which they ſtood, (and from which they received ſtrength,) or the reaſons which were added to their ſupport. And againſt theſe Paſſages he ſeldom offers any reaſons, but they are the matter of his Declamation, and occaſions to ſuggeſt an <hi>Odium</hi> againſt his Opponent. He hath not been able to ſhew any Teſtimony that was cited, to be falſe; or any Inſtance alledged, to be Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent. Therefore the Diſcourſer of Toleration did not think himſelf obliged in point of Reputation to reply to ſuch weak exceptions, becauſe he cannot diſtruſt ſo far his Readers judgment; and for that he thinks that neither his own, nor the Adverſaries credit is of that moment, as to ſpend his time, and concern the World in his writing for it: But he conceives his Obligations and Duties to the Truth, require that he ſhould not deſert it in ſo great an affront, nor ſuffer the People to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed upon by importunate Writers, to think that <hi>Comprchenſion</hi> and <hi>Toleration</hi> are proper methods for the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion,</hi> and fit means for the <hi>Eſtabliſhment</hi> of this <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State.</hi> For theſe are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived to be Originally the Projects of ſuch, who guilty of our late Troubles, have not yet laid down their Enmity to the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhment: Although they may by ſome in the ſimplicity of their hearts, be imbraced for ſuch as they are pretended to be. By theſe laſt ſort of men I would not be miſunderſtood, as if
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:43664:17"/>I intended to obſtruct the way to any who deſires to enter into the Peace and Communion of the Church. For I ſhall e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem it a great mercy, if God ſhould be pleaſed to incline the hearts of thoſe that are Diſſenters, to the true and proper wayes of Peace: and to joyn with us in promoting Truth and Righteouſneſs in the Land, ſo that together with us they may enjoy the Comforts of Gods ſervice, and the Emoluments of the Church. Although I cannot agree with them to think that theſe ways propoſed by them will lead us to ſo happy a ſtate. So that having no animoſity againſt ſuch Perſons, nor even with this mine Adverſary, all other Conſiderations, but thoſe of the Cauſe in Controverſie, being laid aſide, the task will be but ſhort. For avoiding all repetitions as much as may be, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe tedious and nauſeous to the Reader; I ſhall not meddle with what is a freſh printed on the Subject; Becauſe therein the Author ſeems to judicious men <hi>Cantilenam Canere,</hi> repeat other words to the ſame Tune: but ſhall only anſwer to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions he hath made.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 9. <hi>The Diſſenters are guilty of Diſſentions.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>FIrſt he would put of ſo much in the conſideration of To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leration, as ſhews the Subject of it to be <hi>Diſſentions</hi> in <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion</hi> which are remonſtrated to be infamous in their Cauſes, and dreadfull in their Effects, and did therefore require the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates care to obſtruct the ruine they threatned, which could not be done by a Toleration, as appears by Inſtances new and old. All that he would wave with a moſt pitifull Shift of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhing between Diſſentions, and Diſſents, and ſaies, <q>
                     <hi>That thoſe whoſe Liberty is in queſtion, are not touched with that which is Written of the Nature of Diſſentions, with their Cauſes and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences, and the Magiſtrates duty concerning them.</hi>
                  </q> 
                  <hi>Diſſent</hi> indeed and <hi>Diſſentions</hi> differ as the principle, and the actions flowing from that principle, as the Cauſe and the Effects, and may be ſeparated one from the other. But with what faith, and what hope of being believed could this Author ſay, that the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:43664:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>among us are not chargeable with <hi>Diſſention;</hi> Since in the greateſt Schiſms, and moſt confeſſed Diſſentions, there have not been worſe Effects, then the Differences among us have produced. Has not Religion by reaſon of them, been the ſcorne of Atheiſts? What a multitude of Sclanders do the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided parties raiſe upon thoſe from whom they diſſent? What Ruins did they bring upon the State, and what Perſecutions of thoſe who adhered to the Church? Beſides the preſent pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices, ſhew how little the <hi>Non-Conformiſts</hi> reſt in a bare Diſſent from the Publick Rule, when they have and do uſe their ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt endeavours to abrogate that Rule, to repeal the Laws, which eſtabliſh it, When all thoſe Miniſters have relinquiſh'd the places of your Miniſtry, and moſt of them have ſet up private Congregations, by which they forſake the Communion of the Church. What truth or juſtice hath he, that dares deny theſe to be Diſſentions, and that thoſe men are not touched, by what is ſaid of them?</p>
               <p>It appears more fully that theſe men reſted not in a bare Diſſent, ſince their practices upon their Diſſent, proceeded unto Faction, in State, and the ſeveral Kinds and meaſures of Diſſentions were ſo many Factions: which was one of the four reaſons that were given, why a Toleration of them was not for the Intereſt of this Nation. All the reſt the Courteous Reply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er paſſeth over in ſilence, and to this only he ſaies that <hi>They</hi> 
                  <q>
                     <hi>are not ſo Originally and Radically, but by Accident. Some may take advantage to raiſe, and keep up Factions by them.</hi>
                  </q> If they come to be ſuch any way, the manner how they become ſo, is no allevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation to the miſery they bring upon us. But beſides the other reaſons which were before given, it is plain, that there is in Diſſentions of Religion, a natural aptitude to form a Faction; becauſe we ſee Ambitious and Enterprizing men do alwaies make uſe of them, and that with ſucceſs to ſuch an end. For let but the Deſigner pretend the benefit of any one, or more Sects, and then he hath all thoſe that are combined in their Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles, ready for his correſpondence, and united to adminiſter to his Ambition. Therefore thoſe Factious men which lately overthrew our Laws and Government, did but pretend for the <hi>Liberty</hi> of <hi>Godly,</hi> and <hi>Tender Conſciences,</hi> and break down that
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:43664:18"/>Government which was ſet in the Church to reſtrain them, and then all thoſe were preſently devoted to them. And this was done before they did dare <q>
                     <hi>to make that breach between the late King, and Parliament,</hi>
                  </q> and this was the opening of an <hi>Avenue to all our miſeries,</hi> though it was ſome time after, that they did enact a <hi>Toleration for all perſwaſions except Popery and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Gentlemen anſwers not the reaſons, which proved that Diſſentions among us were become Factions, nor did he take notice that all thoſe who have no good will to the State, are ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered among them that are Enemies to the Church. But he only propoſes a different Conſideration of the <hi>Non-Conformiſts,</hi> from <hi>the Papiſts, Theſe laſt</hi> he ſaith, <hi>acknowledge a Foreign Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, and have the refuges of Foreign Princes or States; But the Non-Conformiſt have not.</hi> Suppoſe this were true, yet Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in Religion as we have ſeen, can form a Faction without the help of Foreigners, which by fraud and Force ruined the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient</hi> and <hi>Legal</hi> Government. And when theſe Factious Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons have been diſappointed; they have found Refuge in Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign States, which have reſerved them as fit Inſtruments to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new our Troubles, while they aſſaulted us. The late riſing in <hi>Scotland</hi> doth evidence this; for all thoſe that eſcaped the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Juſtice found entertainment in the Low <hi>Countreys.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 10. <hi>That there is no Stability in the Principles of the Diſſenters.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AFter this he is angry that it was affirmed, <hi>That the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of the Presbyterian Perſwaſion, do not admit of any Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, but may be drawn out to Patronize the wildeſt Sects.</hi> He rejects for this the Teſtimonies of <hi>Archbiſhop Whitgift,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Hooker,</hi> as being their eminent Adverſaries; but he ſaith no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of the argument brought from our own Experience. They were the firſt party among us that broke the Peace, and we know how their principles were flung in their Faces by the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:43664:19"/>Sects, who proceeded further and further upon their po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions. The ground of thoſe Wiſe Mens Obſervation, to whom may be added Dr. <hi>Sanderſon,</hi> was this principle of the Non-Conformiſts, <hi>That the Scripture is,</hi> adaequata agendorum Regula; <hi>ſo as nothing might lawfully be done without expreſs Warrant, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from ſome command, or Example contained therein.</hi> And let judicious men conſider how far this may be drawn.</p>
               <p>But then againſt this he inſtances in the <hi>French, Dutch,</hi> and <hi>Helvetian</hi> Church, which though <hi>Presbyterian</hi> keep themſelves in <hi>Orthodox Unity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this we anſwer, that the Integrity and Unity of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Presbyterian Churches beyond the Sea, do not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude to the ſoundneſs of the principles of that Party among us, no more then their miſcarriages can diſparage thoſe Churches who diſclaim them. For ſome do undertake to prove, that that Party among us, is a particular diſtinct Sect from all of that name beyond the Seas.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pub. Diſp. Salm. Part.</hi> 3. <hi>de Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turg Nuperri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rime exorti ſunt in Anglia Moroſi, ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puloſi,</hi> &amp;c.</note> And they produce this Teſtimony of a Foreign Learned Man <hi>Ludovious Capellus</hi> who ſaith, <hi>There are of late ariſen in</hi> England <hi>certain</hi> Moroſe, Scrupulous, <hi>and too tender (not to ſay Superſtitious) Men, to whom that Liturgie which their Church hath hitherto uſed, ſeems not only reprovable, but they have wholly aboliſhed it, together with the whole</hi> Hierarchical <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of Biſhops: and in its place have ſubſtituted that which they call their Directory.</hi> And however they may agree with thoſe abroad in ſome things: Yet they do not in this prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, which was obſerved to be the reaſon of their <hi>Inſtability.</hi> For 1. The <hi>French</hi> Churche's ſenſe, is expreſt by Mr. <hi>Calvin. We confeſs all and every Church hath juſt Authority to make Laws and Injunctions,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Confeſ. Fidei oblata Caeſari,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Inter opu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcula Calvini. Fatemur tum omnes tum eti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am ſingulas Eccleſias hoc jus habere, ut Leges &amp; ſtatu ta ſibi cond<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>nt Spanhem de La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert Chriſtiana. Theſ.</hi> 23.</note> to Conſtitute a Common Polity among themſelves.</hi> 2. The <hi>Dutch</hi> Church doth not countenance ſuch a principle. For <hi>Span<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemius</hi> a Profeſſor among them ſaith, <hi>Every Church hath a Power that is not abrogated to make Laws,; nor are all humane Traditions to be utterly preſcribed, for Traditions of Doctrine are to be diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed from thoſe of Rites: the Church indeed hath no Legiſlative power about thoſe things; yet it hath about theſe.</hi> 3. As for the <hi>Helvetian</hi> Churches, this Diſcourſer hath been told by the Learned <hi>Durel,</hi> in his Treatiſe <hi>p.</hi> 6. That they are not <hi>Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terian.</hi> For they have a Subordination of Miniſters, as <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſtites,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:43664:19"/>Deans, Canons, Paſtors</hi> who have the Care of Souls, and <hi>Deacons,</hi> as here amongſt us in <hi>England;</hi> they have ſet <hi>forms</hi> of <hi>Prayer, Holy dayes, Organs</hi> and other inſtrumental <hi>Muſick;</hi> and ſure the principles of theſe men as well as their Practices are not Presbyterian, and thoſe Churches that are, have not the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of giddineſs, which are maintained here. If the <hi>Scotch</hi> Church were ſo pure as the Author ſaith, we may aſſign their Purity to their Severities, which frighted all Diſſenters of drawing their principles farther than they would endure.</p>
               <p>In the next place, this Maxim, <hi>That an Indifferent thing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes unlawfull by being commanded;</hi> which was ſaid to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon among the Diſſenters, gives us little hopes of Stability. For ſince ſome things Indifferent, (<hi>i. e.</hi> neither commanded nor forbidden by God) will neceſſarily fall into practice in the Worſhip of God, and through the weakneſs of men there may, and will ariſe contradictory Opinions, and ſo conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly through Intereſt, Humour, and Corruptions, Diſſentions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout them: if there be no power left to the Church to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine thoſe things, and whatſoever ſhe determines doth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore become ſinful, as theſe men imagine, what way is left to us to come to an Eſtabliſhment, and what hopes of Peace and reſt between the contending Parties, when none can determine and enjoyn? That this Maxime is common among them this Author doth not deny, but only gives us the Speech of ſome of them, out of Papers they have printed, Which does not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>own what was imputed to them, but by ſeveral ambages ſeek to hide their ſenſe in that point. But I conceive their judgment in this point is clear under their own hands; when in the Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence at the <hi>Savoy,</hi> Where this Propoſition, <hi>That command which commandeth an Act in it ſelf Lawfull, and no other Act where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by any unjuſt penalty is injoyned, nor any Circumſtance whence directly or</hi> per accidens <hi>any Sin is conſequent which the commander ought to provide againſt, hath in it all things requiſite to the lawfulneſs of a Command, and particularly cannot be guilty of Commanding an Act</hi> per accidens <hi>unlawful, nor of Commanding an Act under an unjuſt Penalty,</hi> was denied by the joynt Conſent of thoſe who diſputed for the Non-Conformiſts. Let this be conſidered <hi>whether this be ſound ſpeech that cannot be proved?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:43664:20"/>
Another ground of diſcouragement from having any hopes of Stability, by admitting their Comprehenſion, is their ſhyneſs to give us the particulars wherein they will reſt, and what will ſatisfy them to an acquieſcence. For though the Diſcourſer ſaith <q>
                     <hi>that the propounded Latitude, leaves out nothing neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to ſecure the Churches Peace:</hi>
                  </q> Yet he refuſes to give us the boundaries of his Latitude; and putting us off as he did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore with theſe General things, neceſſary to Faith and Life, and godly Order, he quarrels the Anſwerer for ſaying <hi>this Eſtabliſhment is not enough for ſettlement, becauſe it doth not ſecure the Churches Peace.</hi> Yet he doth not anſwer any thing to that which proved it, as the Inſtance of the preſent Diſſentions: Wherein though the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> and the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> agree in things neceſſary to <hi>Life, Faith,</hi> and <hi>Order:</hi> Yet we finde no peace betwixt them. To which we may add, that the <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> and <hi>Independents</hi> have a further agreement, yet there was no peace among them, but they mutually writ and preached one againſt the othrr, the firſt declaring and petitioning, that the laſt ſhould not have a Tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and the laſt by Subtlety, and force weakening and expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the firſt to Contempt and Ruin. And therefore ſure there is ſomething elſe neceſſary to Peace.</p>
               <p>It was alſo inſtanced that in Government and Worſhip in both which ſome particulars are not abſolutely neceſſary, there might ariſe Differences. This he doth not diſprove, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies with gravity, <q>
                     <hi>Verily it may much amuſe one to think what that thing ſhould be in the Eccleſiaſtical Polity which is not neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to the Chriſtian Faith, and Life, or Godly Order in the Church; and yet neceſſary to ſecure the Churches Peace.</hi>
                  </q> To take of this amuſement, let it be conſidered how the Great things of Chriſtianity, differ from the peace of the Church. The Principles of <hi>Faith, Good Life and Order</hi> are the Foundation of that Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Society which is the Church. But Peace being as the agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and mutual fitneſs of all the parts of the edifice muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary be of larger extent. There may be breaches in an Houſe, where the Foundation remains firm and entire; and there have been often fierce contentions among <hi>Chriſtians</hi> that yet have agreed in things neceſſary to Salvation, and eſſential to Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:43664:20"/>Worſhip. Theſe truths of Faith, and principles of Life have a continual exiſtence; and though the World ſhould not receive them, and wicked men Contradict them: yet they have ſtill their being in Nature, and are commenſurate with Eternity. But peace may be, and (as experience tells us) is but Temporary. In civil Societies the meaneſt and vileſt Perſons have been a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to make Seditions and Mutinies, even to the overthrow of an Eſtabliſhed Government; and we may finde Schiſms and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions have been made in the Societies of Chriſtians by per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, who through Ignorance have wreſted the Scriptures, and men of perverſe minds whoſe glory was their ſhame, and that alſo upon things of the leaſt moment. Look upon thoſe <hi>Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logues</hi> of <hi>Hereticks</hi> and <hi>Schiſmaticks</hi> that are given us by <hi>Epipha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius, Auguſtine</hi> and <hi>Philaſter,</hi> and you will finde many of them have been not only Infamous in their Authors: but alſo Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible in their Occaſions and grounds of their Separation. Nay, if you will look upon thoſe recorded in Scripture, you may ſoon perceive, from how ſmall occaſions the Contentions, and diviſions did ariſe in the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> about <hi>Paul,</hi> and <hi>Apollos,</hi> and <hi>Cephas,</hi> and <hi>Chriſt,</hi> about the vayling of Women, at Religious Aſſemblies, and thoſe contentions in the celebration of the Sacrament. He that is a conſidering perſon, will not be amuſed to think that there is ſomething neceſſary for the Churches Peace, that is not neceſſary for Faith and good Life and Order.</p>
               <p>We are yet further diſcouraged as to any hopes of <hi>Stability</hi> by the Poſition publiſhed by ſome of the Diſſenters, and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly by this Diſcourſer, <q>
                     <hi>That the Church doth not claim an Infallibility; and therefore ſhe cannot ſettle the Conſcience, by her ſole Warrant, but ſtill leaves room for doubting;</hi>
                  </q> and this he ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges as a reaſon why <q>
                     <hi>ſhe ſhould not preſcribe forms and Rites of Religion,</hi>
                  </q> 
                  <hi>and if ſhe doth, the Conſcience that doth its office will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoſe and concern it ſelf; and it being unſatisfied, Jarrs, and Rents will follow.</hi> This Argument is borrowed from the Popiſh Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, who to reduce the Proteſtants that deny the Infallibility of their Church to an abſurdity, argue that <hi>If the Church be not Infallible, ſhe can propoſe nothing whereof any man may be aſſured it is True or Falſe, but is left to his own Witt and Diſcourſe.</hi> Thus
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:43664:21"/>thoſe who profeſs ſo great an hatred of the Papiſts, do yet take up their Argements for Doctrins and Poſitions, when they will ſerve <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> againſt the Church of <hi>England;</hi> But to prove <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> that <hi>Whoſoever is not infallible, cannot ſettle the</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> that by to <hi>Settle,</hi> this Author underſtood <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> was ſhew'd how many abſurdities muſt needs fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low; for all Government in State, and Families, and the grounds of mutual Commerce, would be overthrown by it. To all which he anſwers by a pitiful Diſtinction, betwixt <hi>Obliging or Binding</hi> the Conſcience, <hi>and ſettling it or leaving no room for doubting; For Conſcience (ſaith he) may be obliged, when it is not ſettled.</hi> By this reply I am now ſatisfied, that his Ignorance is greater then his Malice which I doubted before. For 1. Here he ſuppoſes, that to <hi>ſettle,</hi> ſo as to leave no room for doubting, is the effect of a Law commanded by a juſt and Lawfull Authority, which is falſe. Becauſe many of the Laws of God, and of our Saviour, who are Infallible, did not nor do attain this effect; For there have been, and may be doubts concerning them in the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of holy and good men; And of this we have an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in the Apoſtles. Chriſt had given them a Command <hi>Togo and Preach to all Nations, and Baptize them,</hi> &amp;c. This Command did oblige them to teach the Gentiles: yet St. <hi>Peter</hi> doubted whether he ſhould go to <hi>Cornelius</hi> a Gentile: to ſhow him the things of Chriſt: and was therefore taught by a Viſion not to ſcruple it. The ſame doubt did alſo perplex the other A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles and Brethren, who therefore call'd St. <hi>Peter</hi> to an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, as having done that which he ought not to do, and were not ſettled, that is left not of their doubtings, till St. <hi>Peter</hi> had acquainted them with the Viſion, and miracle of giving the Holy Ghoſt to the <hi>Gentiles.</hi> So that it is evident that to ſettle the Conſcience, is not the effect of Law even from an Infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible Authority; this rather is to be the work of a Teacher, then of a Lawgiver. For the proper and immediate effect of a Law is to <hi>Oblige</hi> and binde, that is, <hi>to impoſe a Neceſſity of Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence upon Men,</hi> who if they do not obey, do ſin, athough they doubt. 2. He has now rendred his opinion far more odious, and of more dangerous, and abſurd conſequence, then it was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. For if whoſoever cannot ſettle the Conſcience, ſo as there
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:43664:21"/>is left no place for doubt, ought not to preſcribe, or give Laws: and if they do give Laws, although the Conſcience is obliged by them, yet it may interpoſe and concern it ſelf, ſo as to cauſe Rents or Jarrs; Then neither an Infallible, nor Fallible Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity can preſcribe Rites, and forms of Religion; becauſe it may ſo be, that the Conſcience may ſtill doubt, and ſo not be ſettled. Now what hopes of ſtability from men of ſuch a perſwaſion? Since the Stability of every Society is founded upon the juſt <hi>Commands</hi> of Superiors, of things within their Power, and the Peoples <hi>Obligation to obey</hi> ſuch Commands: which is overthrown by this poſition: and a doubting Conſcience can ſtrip the Magiſtrate of his Authority, and quit the People from Obedience.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 11. <hi>There was a neceſſity of Enjoyning, and there is alſo of Continuing the Ceremonies.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WHen theſe men have call'd the Churches Authority into Queſtion, then they do her prudence, for making <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junctions that are not at all neceſſary.</hi> To this was ſhewed, that at the beginning of the <hi>Reformation</hi> there was a neceſſity of ſuch In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junctions; becauſe there being Controverſies about them, the Church was to conſult her Peace, and did it, by cutting off ſome Ceremonies, and retaining ſome which were enjoyned to the Common obſervance of all. <hi>That the number of thoſe for Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies was the greateſt, as comprehending all thoſe who ſtaid at home, and did not fly in the time of Queen</hi> Maryes <hi>perſecution.</hi> That they were the greateſt Number the Adverſary did not dare to deny, but without any Teſtimony he ſaith, that <q>
                     <hi>ſuch as Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from the Ceremonies at that time had their Aſſemblies for the Worſhip of God in this Land.</hi>
                  </q> If he had proved this by ſome good Record, it had been more for his credit: but when he only ſaith it, we do him no wrong, if we believe him not, when he aſſerts that which he could not know without a Witneſs.</p>
               <p>It was ſaid alſo, <hi>That the Party againſt Ceremonies was but ſmall,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Eccleſia Reſt. An. Reg. Mar.</hi> 3. p. 59.60.</note> as being but few of thoſe that fled beyond Sea.</hi> For the number of
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:43664:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>thoſe that fled are computed to be but 800. Theſe were di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpers'd in the ſeveral Cities of <hi>Germany</hi> as <hi>Embden, Stratzburg</hi> and <hi>Frankfort</hi> and among the <hi>Switzers</hi> at <hi>Arrow, Zurick,</hi> and <hi>Geneva.</hi> At <hi>Frankfort</hi> it is ſaid, they firſt begun the Alteration of the <hi>Engliſh Liturgy;</hi> thoſe at <hi>Geneva</hi> complyed, it is like, with the Authority of Mr. <hi>Calvin;</hi> yet not ſatisfied with what was done at <hi>Frank fort.</hi> But thoſe of <hi>Stratzburg, Zurick</hi> and <hi>Embden</hi> plainly ſgnifyed to thoſe of <hi>Frankfort,</hi> that they reſolved to maintain the Order of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England;</hi> So that by this account they could be but few. But the Diſcourſer ſaith <q>
                     <hi>it is not true,</hi> Becauſe the ſame Hiſtorian ſaith <hi>that many who were diſaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected to Epiſcepacy, were raiſed to great Preferments.</hi>
                  </q> But the <hi>many</hi> there ſpoken of, were only of the Number that had ſpent their time of Exile in ſuch forreign Churches as had followed the Platform of <hi>Geneva;</hi> and thoſe he reckons to be but <hi>five,</hi> the <hi>Queens Profeſſor</hi> in <hi>Oxford,</hi> the <hi>Lady Margarets</hi> in <hi>Cambridge, Whittingham, Sampſon, and Hardiman.</hi> Of which the two laſt were ſoon turn'd out again as incorrigible Non-Conformiſts: the reſt it ſeems did conform, notwithſtanding their Different Perſwaſions; which was an evidence that they did not think the Ceremonies to be ſo contrary to a good Conſcience, that they were bound either to deſert their Station in the Church, and Miniſtry to Gods Glory; or to diſturb the Peace of Chriſts flock, rather then obſerve thoſe enjoyned Rites. So alſo did thoſe mentioned in the Letter to Mr. <hi>Hooker,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore can be no Inſtances of Non-Conformity, and of diſturbing the Peace in the Church.</p>
               <p>It is alſo true,
<note place="margin">Calv. Ep. Angl. Francofurt. Valde abſurdum eſt, inter fratres ob eandem fidem a patriâ Exu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les ac proſugos diſſidium oriri.</note> and therefore no wrong done, <hi>That the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty againſt Ceremonies, caus'd the Troubles at</hi> Frankfort, <hi>and brought a diſhonour to the Reformation, and Infamy on the Nation;</hi> for Mr. <hi>Calvins</hi> Letter to them at <hi>Frankford,</hi> charges theſe things upon them, and this was Written, <hi>Feb.</hi> 1.31. and Dr. <hi>Cox</hi> with his party, who brought in the Liturgy, came not thither till March 13. following; therefore if Mr. <hi>Calvin</hi> wrote truth, there were troubles among them, before the Conformiſts came thither.</p>
               <p>It is a ſtrange Confidence this Author takes, to deny, <hi>That in the beginning of Queen</hi> Elizabeth<hi>'s Reign, things were ſo ſettled in
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:43664:22"/>the Church of</hi> England, <hi>to pleaſe each party in the aboliſhing ſome, and the retaining other Ceremonies.</hi> For the Compilers them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, (who certainly deſerve in Charity to be credited in what they ſay concerning their own motives and Sentiments,) do af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they had declared the different opinions of men about Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies, ſay, <hi>It was thought expedient not ſo much to have reſpect how to pleaſe and ſatisfy either of theſe parties</hi> (that is, ſingly,) <hi>or gratify their humours, as how to pleaſe God, and to profit them both.</hi> Therefore they intended to <hi>Profit</hi> each party (which in the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles ſenſe is, <hi>to pleaſe our Neighbour to Edification;</hi>) And that <hi>none might be offended, whom Good reaſon might ſatisfy;</hi> They rendred Cauſes why ſome Ceremonies were put away, and ſome retai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. Againſt ſo evident a Teſtimony, he replies, that "<hi>the Ceremonies then aboliſhed, were offenſive to all Proteſtants.</hi> Whereas the compilers themſelves ſay, that there were ſome a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong thoſe whom they would profit, <hi>that did think it a great matter of Conſcience to depart from a piece of the leaſt of their ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed Ceremonies.</hi> Thus this Author hath failed in his attempt to take off the reaſons of neceſſity for the firſt enjoyning of the Ceremonies.</p>
               <p>He is no more ſucceſsfull againſt the Neceſſity of the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance.</hi> For when it had been ſaid, that <hi>They who are for the Church, are unwilling to have the Ceremonies taken away.</hi> He replies, <q>
                     <hi>ſuch as delight in them may enjoy and uſe their Liberty, but let them not lay ſtumbling blocks before others, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangle the Conſcience, or hinder thoſe of a contrary Perſwaſion from the Miniſtry, and from teaching, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </q> This is eaſily ſaid, but he ſhould have alſo proved it practicable. For Inſtance, If in one and the ſame Pariſh the Miniſter be againſt Ceremonies, and the people for them; how ſhall each of theſe enjoy and uſe their Liberties? What contentions and variances, muſt needs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe? If you ſay, the People may make uſe of a Miniſter of the ſame Judgment with themſelves. (1) They cannot do it for all Offices. (2) This muſt lay a conſtant ground of aliena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and ſo of Quarrelling betwixt People and Miniſter, and betwixt the Miniſters themſelves. How can this Writer for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get that this was a frequent Caſe in the late troubles, almoſt in all Pariſhes? This therefore is to multiply diviſions; that
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:43664:23"/>at laſt muſt overthrow all. And there is no conſidering Perſon but ſees a neceſſity that all Miniſters ſhould be bound to the ſame Rule.</p>
               <p>Another reaſon for continuing the Ceremonies was, becauſe it would be in vain to comply with them, who will never be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied. To this he anſwers, <q>
                     <hi>With what ſoberneſs can this be ſaid, when hitherto the Diſſenters were never tryed with any Relaxation, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </q> But with what truth can he ſay they were never tryed? When they had a Relaxation at the Kings firſt coming home; and it was left to them, to conform in what they could have no ſcruple of Conſcience, yet this did not ſatisfy them. But he had ſaid before, <q>
                     <hi>That ſome of them did comply with the Kings deſire.</hi>
                  </q> Yet he doth not tell us who, or how many; and in deed when this was objected to their Friends that laboured for an Indulgence for them, they could not give an account of any conſiderable number that did ſo. <q>
                     <hi>Others</hi> (he ſaith) <hi>did not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps for the prevention of Scandal.</hi>
                  </q> And we ſay perhaps, The ſame <hi>Perhaps</hi> to prevent a Scandal among their own Party, whoſe Spirits they have imbittered with an hatred of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> may ſtill prevail upon them to be-unſatisfied. So that the Honour of the Church and State muſt be proſtituted, by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealing their Laws and Injunctions, to the Fortuitous pleaſure of them that do not conform. Beſides, this Author will not give us the bounds of his deſired Latitude, nor aſſure us where that Party will ſtand; How far we muſt go to ſatisfy all the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Sects, and how many will be gained; all theſe things are requiſite to aſſure us, that they intend to be ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed.</p>
               <p>It was alſo ſaid that the Imputations of <hi>Idolatry, Superſtition</hi> and <hi>Antichriſtianiſm</hi> to the things enjoyned, perſwade us not eaſily to part with them, as being ſo guilty. Theſe Calumnies have been engraven with Swords, and written in blood; and to renounce what we believe to be innocent, as criminal, is plainly to declare that we have no love to the Truth, that we tacitly condemn what we approve, and we ſhould likewiſe Calumni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate all thoſe whoſe Communion we pretend to, the former Church, who did obſerve them as indifferent.</p>
               <p>The Diſcourſer does not deny, that theſe Calumnies have
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:43664:23"/>been raiſed, nor doth he condemn the ſlanderers, but he ſayes, <q>
                     <hi>Shall their value be ſo exhanced, as to be thought of more worth then the Unity of the Church.</hi>
                  </q> To which we anſwer, That though we account the Church's <hi>Unity</hi> to be of an infinite Value above them, yet we cannot promiſe our ſelves to procure her Unity by a thing that is not juſt in it ſelf; that is by juſtifying falſe imputations in taking away, what we, and other Chriſtians have thought clear and praiſe-worthy. The expedient which he hath propoſed, for ſalving the Churches honour, by her decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, <q>that <hi>ſhe remits her injunctions in compliance with weak con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences,</hi>
                  </q> Will be an envidence of her very great weakneſs: un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs thoſe <hi>Weak</hi> Conſciences declare alſo, that ſhe hath not been Idolatrous, Superſtitious, or Antichriſtian in her former enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of them, and that the things contended about, were but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different, (for ſo St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s declaration concerning abſtaining from meats, did conclude both ſides to ſuch apprehenſions of them) As alſo that they confeſs, and bewail the Schiſm which they have already made; and take ſhame to themſelves, for all thoſe practices which they have done againſt the Church. Such a Declaration as this may ſerve to repair the Churches Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and move her to remit her Injunctions, to men that give ſuch evidence of having tender Conſciences. But the Non-Conformiſts are ſo far from ſuch a declaration, that this Author ſayes in the next <hi>Section,</hi> that <q>
                     <hi>They account theſe things not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different but unlawful.</hi>
                  </q> So that this expedient will only caſt ſhame on the Church, and leave them to the boaſtings of their own Godlineſs.</p>
               <p>It was alſo urged for the Continuance of thoſe Injunctions, <hi>that a War was undertook to remove them;</hi> and that if now they were yielded up to the pleaſure of thoſe that fought a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, they would in the next place charge all the blood of that War upon the Church, and her Party. To this he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies, that <q>
                     <hi>it is eaſier ſaid then proved, that the late War was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaken to remove the Ceremonies.</hi>
                  </q> To which we ſay, that if there was any Faith in the Declarations of thoſe that managed the late War, or in the Sermons of thoſe who were to encourage the People to it, and did therefore beg for money and men, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For Jeſus Chriſt, and thoſe that did denounce Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:43664:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>from the Lord, on ſuch as not come forth to his aſſiſtance againſt the mighty, If thoſe Articles about Religion which were propoſed in every Treaty of Peace had any truth; then it is as eaſily proved as ſaid, that That War was undertaken, (though not ſolely) to remove the things in difference betwixt the Church and the Diſſenters; and it is an Impudence, equal to their other practices, to deny it. And as this is clear, ſo it is as clear, that they charged upon his <hi>Late Murther'd Majeſty,</hi> all the blood of that War; becauſe he had made conceſſions in the like nature, and we have nor eaſon to expect otherwiſe now. I'll leave this Author to pleaſe himſelf in the Malice and Envy of the argument he hath made from theſe my premiſes.</p>
               <p>Although the controverted Ceremonies are no Foundation of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> yet far leſs changes, in the laſt edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>Liturgy</hi> have been taken by <hi>Popiſh Prieſts,</hi> (to my own knowledge,) as advantages to brand her of Inconſtancy, to diſſwade ſome ignorant perſons, to forſake her, as ſtill various: and to come over to their Church, which was founded upon a Rock. And this was urged as a reaſon not to take them away. In ſtead of a ſatisfying anſwer, this odious inference is made. <q>
                     <hi>It ſeems that greater care muſt be taken, that the Papiſts be not offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, then that many thouſands of honeſtly minded Proteſtants ſhould be relieved.</hi>
                  </q> Is there no difference betwixt taking care, <hi>that no advantage be given to Popiſh Prieſts to ſeduce Proteſtants,</hi> and a taking care <hi>that the Papiſts be not offended?</hi> The Author knows there is a difference, but he was to gratify his Hatred, and he hath done it. The like deſign of expoſing his Adverſary to the <hi>Odium</hi> of a kindneſs to the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> he had practiced, <hi>Sect.</hi> 8. For when the grounds which he had laid of denying a Toleration to the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, were applied to the other Diſſenters. He neglects to ſhow the Diſparity; or that the application was injurious: but makes this Demand. <q>
                     <hi>What greater advantage can be given to the Papiſts, then that a Proteſtant Writer ſhould declare, That ſo great a part of Proteſtants, are equally envolved with them in thoſe heinous Crimes,</hi> &amp;c?</q> The anſwer is obvious, For they that did thoſe things, have given the Popiſh Party a far greater advantage. He that declares it, doth tell them no more then what they have been told before, even by Forreign Proteſtants; who
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:43664:24"/>deteſted ſuch Acts of thoſe men, who among us falſly pretend to the honour of that name. Beſides, he that declares it, doth tell them no more then what they know before. Do you think the Papiſts had loſt their Sences and Reaſon? Did they not ſee a Rightfull Prince, firſt driven by Arms from his Throne; and afterwards hurried to the Slaughter? Nor do I think that the Crimes of thoſe men, or the declaring of them, to be more a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach to the Proteſtant Profeſſion; then they are to Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity, to which they and other Criminals do equally pretend. Thoſe that were true and knowing Chriſtians, did then ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hor thoſe practices; and do not take the mentioning of them for a reproach to themſelves.</p>
               <p>There is no reaſon that the Diſcourſer ſhould be aſtoniſhed at the laſt Reaſon, That <hi>Diſſentions about things indifferent, have neceſſitated the Church to make thoſe injunctions.</hi> For it was appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent before, in the reaſons that the Compilers of the Liturgy gave; That becauſe there were different perſwaſions of the Ceremonies; therefore ſome were enjoyned. And in this our Church did no otherwiſe then the Catholick Church hath done in like Caſes. I ſhall give him one Inſtance, I might give more. The Diſſenſions in the primitive times, about the Feaſt of <hi>Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> moved the Council of <hi>Nice</hi> to determine and enjoyn one time for it to all Chriſtians; for no other reaſon, but that there might be an <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>i.e.</hi> an agreement among Chriſtians. Let lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and good men judge, on which ſide lyes the Animoſities: who hath the beſt Pretentions to Equity, Charity, and good Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 12. <hi>Non-Conformiſts are leſs capable of Comprehenſion than other men of Different Opinions, who are tolerated in the Church of</hi> England.</head>
               <p>THe Contenders for <hi>Comprehenſion,</hi> and <hi>Toleration,</hi> do urge, that the <hi>Indulgence of the Church of</hi> England, <hi>to men differently perſwaded in the points of Predeſtination, Free-will, &amp;c. may be extended to them.</hi> In anſwer to which it was ſaid,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:43664:25"/>The Moderation of the Church as to thoſe, was grounded upon the Difference betwixt thoſe Diverſe Opinions in the point of Predeſtination: and the Diſſenſions about her Orders and Ceremonies, That thoſe were Difficulties in all Ages and all Religions. Theſe required but one ſingle Reſolution, whether an indifferent Ceremony might be enjoyned? To this he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers, <q>
                     <hi>That the matters of Inconformity are not things only indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, but accounted by them unlawfull.</hi>
                  </q> This is to beg the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion; for if they be indifferent, they cannot be unlawful; and it is not enough to account them unlawful: but they muſt prove them to be ſo, which the Author wiſely declines.</p>
               <p>But then he queſtions the truth of that Aſſertion; <hi>That the Diſſenters cannot name one Church beſides ours, in which there was a Schiſm made for a Ceremony.</hi> Yet he makes the aſſertion good, for he hath not, nor can he name one particular Church as ours, in which, for a Ceremony, there was made a Schiſm, and a diviſion of the members, from one another, and of one part from their Paſtors and Biſhops. He ſaid indeed, <q>
                     <hi>That a great Rent was made in the Chriſtian Church throughout the World, about a Ceremony the time of Celebrating the Feaſt of Eaſter.</hi>
                  </q> Which if true, is not pertinent; for that Diſſention was not betwixt Members of a particular Church: but betwixt the <hi>Afiatick</hi> and all other Churches. Secondly, there was no Schiſm made; For <hi>frenaeus</hi> ſhew'd plainly that the former Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> did preſerve their communion with the <hi>Aſiaticks.</hi> And although <hi>Victor</hi> had been ſo hot as to publiſh an excommunication; yet the Diſſent of the other Biſhops from ſuch a courſe, ſoon hindred the effects of it, as to a Schiſm.</p>
               <p>There are alſo differences Tolerated in the Church of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> but not of thoſe Effects, and Principles, as are the Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions about the <hi>Diſciplinarian</hi> Way. The <hi>Arminians</hi> and <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arminians</hi> never broke Communion among themſelves, nor that of the Church; they loaded indeed one another with horrid Conſequences of <hi>Pelagianiſm</hi> on one ſide, and <hi>Manicheiſm</hi> and <hi>Stoiciſm</hi> on the other; but ſtill kept a common Reverence to the Church, and appealed to her Articles. The differences of <hi>Bowing</hi> or not <hi>Bowing,</hi> of uſeing <hi>Conceived,</hi> or <hi>Bidding</hi> Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, never ſo far prevailed as to harſh cenſures, Therefore
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:43664:25"/>the Church was never put to a neceſſity to conſult her peace by determining, and enjoyning. But it hath been far otherwiſe in the Differences of the <hi>Conformiſts</hi> and <hi>Non-Conformiſts,</hi> theſe laſt have all wayes attempted the deſtroying of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, altering the Worſhip, and Diſcipline of it; have gather'd, and do gather, ſeparate Congregations. They re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed the Publick Communion as a continuing in <hi>Babylon;</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted their own way as the Kingdom of Chriſt, and by theſe courſes did bring an Univerſal Confuſion. Which brought a neceſſity upon the Church to determine, and to ſecure her ſelf, by hindring ſuch perſons from the Opportunities of divulging theſe their Opinions in a Conſtant Miniſtery. As for thoſe that have only different Apprehenſions from her in theſe things, and yet do ſecure her by ſubſcriptions from troubling her, they alwaies did, and may ſtill be admitted to the Offices and Emolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in her.</p>
               <p>There is yet another reaſon which makes us afraid of a <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion,</hi> and that by it we cannot attain the pretended ends of <hi>Unity</hi> and <hi>Peace,</hi> Becauſe it will permit men of ſuch Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictory Perſwaſions, to different Practices, in almoſt all the daily Offices of Religion; (Which cannot be ſaid of the other Differences which are tolerated in our Church.) And to think that ſuch men on both ſides will content themſelves in their own Opinions, and reſt ſatisfyed in the Liberty they enjoy, without attempts upon their Oppoſites, is <hi>vainly</hi> to ſuppoſe that <hi>Men will be wiſe on both ſides.</hi> To which it is replied, that <q>
                     <hi>We need ſuppoſe no more but that the State and chief Guides of the Church be wiſe; that the Eminent Perſons of both ſides be Mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and Prudent, and the Publick conſtitution ſo well Stated and ſettled, as to be able to Curb the Imprudent, and to encourage the well adviſed.</hi>
                  </q> If this Author did conſider how tender, and nice a thing Peace is; how hardly it is kept, while men have different Luſts, divided Intereſts, and bad Hopes; how eaſily it is broken, even by the loweſt and vileſt parts of a Society; and that in deſpight of the wiſeſt Princes, and greateſt Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellors, he would alſo grant that it is as neceſſary that the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations of it ſhould be laid in the minds of the Community,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:43664:26"/>as well as in the breaſts of Great men, and the Rules of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>The firſt <hi>Maſſacre</hi> of the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> in <hi>France</hi> began from the Rabble. For as the <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Guiſe</hi> was paſſing by <hi>Vaſſey</hi> in <hi>Champaigne</hi> (where the proteſtants by the Edict of <hi>January,</hi> 1562. had the Liberty of their Religion,) and heard their Bell which called the <hi>Profeſtants</hi> to the place of their Worſhip; He went into the Town, intending by his Preſence only, without any Violence to diſſolve their meeting, But ſtaying in the Streets, to talk with the Officers of the Town, his Lackques and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour part of his Train (which then uſed to be very great with the <hi>French</hi> Nobility,) went before to the Place where the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants were aſſembled, and there firſt beginning with revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, and anſwered in the ſame manner by the Proteſtants, they proceeded to fling ſtones, and after that alighting from their Horſes with their Swords and Piſtols they aſſaulted that unarmed company; and although the ſhreeks and cryes of Women and Children for help, had brought the <hi>Duke</hi> to the place, yet neither his intreaties, nor threatnings could prevail till all the Proteſtants were either ſlain, or fled. Where the Hiſtorian ſaith, there were 60. kill'd, and 200 wounded, the <hi>Duke</hi> himſelf having been hurt in his Face, while he ſought to appeaſe the Tumult. The wiſdom of States and Guides can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not poſſibly prevent popular commotions which are ſuddain and violent. Beſides the Diſſenters from our Church render the State and Guides of the Church uncapable of hindring the ſad effects of differences in Religion. One party denies that the Guides of the Church can command an indifferent thing. The other Party which are theſe of the Congregational Way, deny that the State hath any power in things of Religion, What then ſhall become of the wiſdome of the State, and Guides of the Church, and well Stated conſtitution to form or keep Peace? Moreover, there was another reaſon given, which this Author mentions but doth not anſwer. <hi>That Diſſenters upon Conſcience will be prevailed with by the ſame Conſcience, to endeavour the propagation of their own way in theſe differences,</hi> to the Depreſſion of others; Eſpecially when their apprehenſions of their own way, put ſuch a value upon them as to render them the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt,</hi>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:43664:26"/>the <hi>Worſhipping of God in the Spirit.</hi> And on the other ſide they think their Oppoſites to be guilty of thoſe crimes againſt which God hath declared his jealouſie. This is a thing daily ſeen in all the divided Parties, and then what hopes can we have of Peace? The Replyer gives no other anſwer but this. <q>
                     <hi>If ſome offer to diſturb the Peace, can no Rule of Government reſtrain them?</hi>
                  </q> The Magiſtrate in this caſe can do nothing but by <hi>Force;</hi> and that is declaimed againſt, as <hi>Compulſion</hi> of <hi>Faith, Tyranny,</hi> and <hi>Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution.</hi> Beſides, the Supreme Magiſtrate may be often diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from his cares of theſe things, by the more preſſing Exigen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of State; and ſo not be able to take notice of the firſt aſſaults on the Peace, till the wounds of it becomes dangerous, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt incurable.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 13. <hi>Neceſſity only can juſtify a Toleration, and a ſtanding Army muſt make it ſafe.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THis Poſition had been aſſerted, <hi>that Only Neceſſity can give colour to Toleration; For that it is by the Confeſſion of all, one of thoſe things that are not good in their own nature.</hi> Which the Diſcourſer ſaith, "<hi>he cannot yield unto,</hi> but he would not have been ſo Pertinacious, if he had conſidered that Unity in Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is commanded us, that we are enjoyn'd to practice all the methods of it, as that which is moſt for the Glory of Chriſt, and the honour of Religion; that at beſt it is but our infirmity, if we are not all of one heart and one Soul: and who dare de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, but that it were beſt that all Chriſtians were ſo? But when after all Eſſayes we cannot root them out, then we muſt bear with them, yet ſo as to ſet bounds to the Diſſenters, and cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſcribe Diſſentions, which I conceive is a <hi>Toleration;</hi> So that this is the laſt reſort, and therefore is like <hi>War</hi> and <hi>Oaths</hi> which nothing but Neceſſity can juſtify. But this Author thinks it <hi>a branch of Brotherly Love.</hi> We ſay <hi>Brotherly Love</hi> may be uſed indeed, in the firſt ariſing of Diſſentions, as means to allay them, and to prevent a Toleration, or may be exerciſed in it: but there is no reaſon to think it is a Toleration.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:43664:27"/>
In the next place be quarrels, that it was ſaid, that <hi>we want an Inſtance of the ſafety of Toleration, in any Nation, where the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Governour had not an Army to Circumſcribe, and confine the heats of Diſſenters in Religion to their own breaſts, and keep off the deſtructive effects of Schiſm.</hi> In ſtead of anſwering this, by ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an Inſtance; for I appealed to the Practice of the <hi>Ancient Emperours</hi> and <hi>Modern Princes</hi> and <hi>States.</hi> He replies, <q>that <hi>ſuch a Maxim, makes little for the ſafety and Liberty of True Religion,</hi> and then rants againſt it <hi>as an injury done to Proteſtants that live under Popiſh Princes, and as the dictate of Prejudice and Partiality.</hi>
                  </q> This is a very uncouth way of anſwering arguments, 'and it is a brutiſh way of conſidering things as to our preſent advantage, or as they poſſibly may be uſed, without any reſlections on the former practices of Mankind. But I ſhall take off the <hi>Odium</hi> he uſually flings when he hath no reaſon to return, by aſſuring him, that a <hi>Standing Army</hi> is neceſſary to ſuppreſs thoſe Tumults which often on a ſuddain like Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quakes do ariſe among the diſſenting Parties, which if not immediately cruſh'd, may gather ſtrength, while a force is to be formed againſt them. And that ſuch Tumults may ariſe from that party which is <hi>Eſtabliſhed</hi> by Law as well as the <hi>Tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,</hi> who may be inſolent in their own power and advantages, and ſeek to violate the Faith of the Prince which is given to the Tolerated. And therefore the Sword of a <hi>Standing Army</hi> is to be a terrour not only to the Tolerated, but alſo to the Eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed Parties, and ſecures the ſafety and Liberty of the true Religion, if either be true. And although the <hi>French</hi> King hath more aſſurance of the Loyalty of his <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Subjects (while they retain the true doctrine of <hi>Proteſtantiſm which is not to acknowledge any power above Soveraign Princes,</hi> either of the <hi>Pope</hi> as the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> or of the <hi>People,</hi> as our <hi>Diſſenters,</hi>) then of the <hi>Popiſh party;</hi> yet there is a Neceſſity upon him to maintain conſtant Forces to keep both Parties in peace, and to ſecure the Proteſtants who are weak and leſs Numerous, from the daily attempts of the Romiſh Prieſts to ſtir up the People to a Maſſacre. Therefore <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>fourth</hi> of <hi>France</hi> thought it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for the ſecurity of his Proteſtant Subjects (who had ſhewed themſelves loyal to his Intereſt) to allow them ſeveral
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:43664:27"/>ſtrong fortified Towns for their Security in all <hi>France,</hi> which were called <hi>Les Villes de ſuretè;</hi> whereof <hi>Rochel</hi> was chief. And eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Prince hath need of an Army to make good his promiſe, if he once hath paſſed his word for a Toleration. And although To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leration is not the reaſon of a ſtanding Army among the <hi>Dutch;</hi> yet a <hi>Standing Army</hi> ſecures it.</p>
               <p>The other paſſages out of the <hi>Diſcourſe of Toleration,</hi> which he afterwards mentions, are matters of his remarks and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, rather than of his objections; and therefore I ſhall no more concern the Reader with them. He concludes with a Complaint of the <hi>Anſwerer,</hi> that <q>
                     <hi>he hath uſed Many hard ſpeeches againſt him, and charged him with Malice.</hi>
                  </q> Do but conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Paſſages, and judg betwixt him and me, and if the charge be not true, I ſhall not be aſhamed to crave his pardon. I wonder how he can ſay, that <q>
                     <hi>he hath written theſe things, as knowing that the Judge ſtandeth before the Door;</hi>
                  </q> for ſurely ſuch a Conſideration would have perſwaded him to another frame of Spirit. But howſoever, I do in ſincerity commend him to the <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Mercy</hi> of him, who is the <hi>Great Shepherd of the Flock,</hi> who hath commanded us <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Unity;</hi> And who ſhall <hi>One day judg the World in Righteouſneſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 6. line 35. for eanm r. mean. p. 17. l. 19. r. baſeneſs p. 18. l. 34. f. that r. the, p. 23. l. 4. r. Kindneſs, p. 27. l. 23. r. contraries, p. 32. l. 13. f. your r. their, p. 35. f. of r. from, l. 38. r. reproved, p. 40. l. 36. f. either r. thither p. 44. l. 1. r. did not.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
